<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Invisible realities, the real Christian's greatest concernment in several sermons on 2 Cor. 4. 18 / by Henry Pendlebury ...</title>
            <author>Pendlebury, Henry, 1626-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54010</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6886</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12588004</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12588004</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63794</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54010)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63794)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 674:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Invisible realities, the real Christian's greatest concernment in several sermons on 2 Cor. 4. 18 / by Henry Pendlebury ...</title>
                  <author>Pendlebury, Henry, 1626-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xvi, 127 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for Ann Unsworth of Manchester, and sold by Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Dr. Williams' Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, IV, 18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63794:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63794:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Inviſible Realities THE REAL CHRISTIAN'S Greateſt Concernment. In ſeveral SERMONS On 2 COR. 4.18.</p>
            <p>By HENRY PENDLEBURY, A. M. late Miniſter of the Goſpel at
<hi>Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire;</hi> Author of the <hi>Plain Repreſentation of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Ann <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſworth</hi> of <hi>Mancheſter;</hi> and ſold by <hi>Jonathan Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.
1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63794:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:63794:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>HUGH</hi> Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> of <hi>Parham.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE favourable Aſpect your Lordſhip is pleaſed to afford to the living Miniſters and Members of Chriſt, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages me to addreſs unto your Honour theſe worthy remains of a Reverend Miniſter now with God. And as I would humbly implore your Lordſhip's kind and noble Patronage to theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, ſo I do with the profoundeſt Deference and Submiſſion, commend them to your Peruſal and Practice. Your Lordſhip is not without a juſt Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the Caution and Vigilancy which they more eſpecially ſtand in need of, who poſſeſs an high Station, and manage great Concerns in this viſible World, leſt they ſhould be diverted thereby from ſeeking that which is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible and Eternal. The Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons preſented in the following Sheets, will contribute no ſmall Aſſiſtance to your Lordſhip's Chriſtian endeavours in this weighty Affair: They do not only <pb n="iv" facs="tcp:63794:3"/> make future Inviſible Things a match to cope with thoſe that have the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a Senſible, Viſible Preſence; but, if duly attended to, may by the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, give them a victorious Sway and Empire in the Thoughts and Affections of Men.</p>
            <p>That your Lordſhip's Conduct may entirely correſpond with the Profeſſion you make of a moſt holy Religion, and with the clear Knowledg of Divine Things, wherewith it hath pleaſed God to endow you; that to your noble Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction and great Abilities, you may add many honourable Atchievements, and happy Performances, for the Glory of God, the Good of his Church, and the Proſperity of your Native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to the everlaſting Honour of your Perſon and Family in this World, and to the Salvation of your precious Soul in the World to come, is and ſhall be the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip, Your Lordſhip's moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant, <hi>JOHN CHORLTON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="v" facs="tcp:63794:3"/>
            <head>A Brief ACCOUNT OF THE LIFE OF THE AUTHOR.</head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Henry Pendlebury,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Author of the enſuing Diſcourſe, was born the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>May 1626,</hi> at
<hi>Jokin</hi> in <hi>Bury</hi> Pariſh in <hi>Lancaſhire:</hi> His excellent Memory is owing to the following Account. He was from his Childhood of a ſolid and reſerved Spirit; there did then appear in him an averſneſs to Vanity, and an inclination to Seriouſneſs; he had an aptneſs for, and love to Learning, and purſued it with great Cloſeneſs and Diligence. There then ſeemed to be an early Foundation laid in him, upon which afterwards a high Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:63794:4"/> of Learning and Goodneſs was to be erected. He was at ſeveral Schools, but perfected for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity at <hi>Bury</hi> School. After he had taken his Degrees at
<hi>Cambridg,</hi> he returned into <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and preached his firſt Sermon at <hi>Aſhworth</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Midleton, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt 16. 1648.</hi> where afterwards he ſpent ſome time as Probationer in the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>He was ſet apart to the Office and Work of the Miniſtry at
<hi>Turton</hi>-Chappel, in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of <hi>Bolton</hi> in the <hi>Moors, Octob.</hi> 3d <hi>1650.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reverend Miniſters that inveſted him in the Miniſterial Office, were Mr. <hi>John Tilſley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Pitts,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Jonathan Scolefield,</hi> Mr. <hi>Toby Furneſs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robert Bath.</hi> They who were preſent, obſerved him to make his Ordination-Vows and Promiſes with great Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of Spirit.</p>
            <p>After his Ordination, he preached near a Year at
<hi>Horrigde</hi>-Chappel, in the Pariſh of <hi>Dean.</hi> From thence he removed to <hi>Holcombe</hi> Chappel in the Pariſh of <hi>Bury, October 16.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>651.</hi> where he laboured hard in his Maſter's Work, till he was excluded from the publick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof in that Place on Black
<hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew</hi> Day <hi>1662.</hi> when about <hi>2000</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters were turned out for Non-conformity. The Adjacent Miniſters and People had him in high Eſtimation for his Life and Labours. When he was there, he had a Call from the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at <hi>Ringley,</hi> but they at <hi>Holcombe</hi> being ſenſible what a burning and ſhining Light he <pb n="vii" facs="tcp:63794:4"/> was amongst them, would not be brought to give up their Title to him. He had a large meaſure of natural Gifts and Parts, which furniſhed him with great promptneſs and readineſs for all his Miniſterial Performances; but they did not render him the leſs ſtudious, for he would not ſerve the Lord with that which coſt him nothing. Much of his Time was ſpent in his Cloſet, where he gave himſelf to Prayer, Reading, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation: This was the only Place upon Earth, where he took the greateſt Pleaſure, next to his Pulpit. He did not concern himſelf in any ſecular Affairs pertaining to his Family, but devolved the whole Management of them upon his vertuous Conſort. All his Sermons both as to the Heads and Enlargement of them, were premeditated and penned, and afterwards preached with little variation without the help of his Notes; which manifeſted, beſide the ſtrength of his Memory, the vaſtneſs of his Pains to fix them therein, conſidering the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Matter, and the number of the Texts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them.</p>
            <p>So great was his Induſtry, that in his Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when there were ſome ſmall Hopes of his Recovery, he ſet himſelf to ſtudy a new Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſutable to his own and his Hearers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Before his Excluſion from this Work in Publick, beſide his conſtant Preaching every Lord's Day at <hi>Holcombe</hi> among his People, he preached much to other Congregations both far and near, in the Country which had their
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:63794:5"/> Monthly Exerciſes; and after he was ſilenced, he continued as Laborious in Preaching as before. And indeed the Diſſenting Party of Proteſtants in all the Pariſhes adjacent to him, were very deſirous of his Labours amongst them; and he was free to ſpend, and be ſpent for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of their Souls good. He was ever mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of his Ordination-Vow, and could not think that any Power upon Earth could null his Commiſſion which he had received from Chriſt to preach the Goſpel. He was moſt eminent for Humility, Meekneſs, and Self-denial; herein he ſhined above his Fellows.</p>
            <p>His Modeſty was ſuch, that tho he was one of the talleſt of his Brethren for Miniſterial Attainments and Performances, yet he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally eſteem himſelf the leaſt of them all: his Humility caſt ſuch a Vail over all his Abilities, that he could not diſcern them though they were very conſpicuous to others. He was able to maintain the Truths of the Goſpel committed to his Truſt, againſt the Oppoſers and Subver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of them. The Controverſies both as to Faith and Worſhip, between the Proteſtants and Papiſts, were throughly underſtood by him; his ſmall Treatiſe of
<hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is a ſufficient Evidence of his Ability to defend the Proteſtant Cauſe: And he has left behind him another piece on the <hi>Sacrifice of the Maſs,</hi> not inferior to it in Worth and Excellency.</p>
            <p>He had a Tranſcript of all thoſe Divine Truths and Graces upon his own Heart, which <pb n="ix" facs="tcp:63794:5"/> he diſcloſed unto others; the ſcope of all his Studies, Prayers, and Sermons, was directed by him to the ſaving of himſelf, and thoſe that heard him. And in his Converſation were ſo expreſſed the Power and Life of all his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Acts in a Holy Imitation of his Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, as did ſhew him to be really perſwaded in his Heart that there was more than ordinary Care required of him to keep himſelf in all Reſpects pure from the Blood of Souls: and the Lord who is the ſearcher and trier of the Heart, and who loves Truth of Grace in the inward parts, did crown his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Endeavours with great Succeſs. He did not run in vain, nor labour in vain, nor ſpend his Strength for nought; but he had Seals of his Miniſtry all along, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the cloſe thereof; and the Lord ordered it ſo wiſely in his Providence, that ſometimes the notice, or the ſaving Succeſs of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry was then brought unto him, when it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced moſt to his inward Support and Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Then (to give one Inſtance of many) when he was baniſhed by the <hi>Oxford</hi> Act, at the firſt Houſe he took up his Lodging as a poor Exile from his own Home, he who ſaluted him as his Spiritual Father, related to him that he was the Inſtrument of his Converſion, by preaching a Lecture-Sermon at <hi>Leigh</hi> Church. Mr.
<hi>Nathaniel Hilton</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> gave a Stipend for a Weekly Lecture at <hi>Bolton</hi> every Monday, of the moſt eminent Miniſters in the <pb n="x" facs="tcp:63794:6"/> County, to four in their Courſes, among whom this worthy Servant of Chriſt was choſen one, other two were Mr. <hi>Roger Baldwin,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Henry Newcome,</hi> who are both ſometime ſince removed by Death. <hi>Ceaſe Lord, by whom ſhall</hi> Jacob <hi>ariſe, for he is ſmall?</hi> He was a great redeemer of his Time, there was not ſo much as a Day ſpent by him in Idleneſs; the ſenſe of unſeen things was ſo deeply impreſt upon his Spirit, as made him fill every Leaf in the Book of his Life, with thoſe great and weighty Works which were incumbent on him in his Place.</p>
            <p>When Perſons that had been converted by his Miniſtry gave notice to him thereof, he would with great Humility lift up his Eyes and Hands towards Heaven, and ſay, Lord, who am I, that I ſhould be ſo far honoured as to be the Inſtrument in the converting of one Soul!</p>
            <p>He was Eminent for Contempt of the World, he never ſought great Places for himſelf, and when they were offered him, he declined them; he was content to move in an obſcure and low Sphere, ſo he might but be an Inſtrument of doing good to Souls; he would not be drawn nor driven away to any other Buſineſs, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in his laborious Courſe of Preaching twice every Lord's Day, adminiſtring the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Monthly.</p>
            <p>He was a conſtant Mourner for the Sins of the Nation; and was greatly concerned for the riſing Generation, and bent his Diſcourſes t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſtabliſh them in the true Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="xi" facs="tcp:63794:6"/>He welcomed his laſt Sickneſs with deep Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Will of God.</p>
            <p>He expreſſed his Contentedneſs, if his Lord and Maſter whom he ſerved with his Spirit in the Goſpel, had any more Work for him to accompliſh in the Church below; but if not, he was willing to depart, deſirous to have his own Bleſſedneſs among the Saints above, and to be with Chriſt as being far better.</p>
            <p>He had little pain in the beginning of his Sickneſs, and was much in bleſſing of God for dealing ſo gently with him, and carrying on his long Viſitation with ſo great eaſe to him. He kept his reſigned Frame to the Will of his Heavenly Father, and ſaid, I have had more Time to work for my own and others Souls, than I made accompt of when I was Young, and ſo if God have no more Work for me to do, I am free to go to my Reſt; I have had enough of Living, and am filled and ſatisfied with this Life upon Earth.</p>
            <p>There came Friends from all Places where he had preached to viſit him, to whom he always dropped ſome word of ſutable Counſel. He ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed thoſe who told him they were converted by his Miniſtry, to give God the Glory, and to walk worthy of the Vocation wherewith they were called.</p>
            <p>He exhorted thoſe who had profited, and were built up in Grace by his Labours, to go on their way rejoicing, tho they ſhould ſee his Face no more.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="xii" facs="tcp:63794:7"/>He cautioned rich and trading Profeſſors to take heed that they loſt not their Souls in a croud and hurry of earthly Buſineſs; he charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to remember the Saying of Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Moor,</hi> there is a great Truth in it, as well as a Scum of Wit;
<q>There is a Devil that is termed Buſineſs, that carrieth more Souls with him to Hell, than all the Devils in Hell beſide.</q> O beware of the Devil; when you come to be in my Condition, your full Bags, your full Shops, and full Houſes, will ſtand you in no ſtead.</p>
            <p>Some of his Reverend Brethren in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry did viſit him, with whom he freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed, and whom he always deſired to pray with him as he did all his other Chriſtian Friends; and amongst the reſt Reverend Mr. <hi>O. H.</hi> was with him, and in his Diſcourſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded theſe Queries here inſerted, to which be returned with great compoſedneſs of Mind the following Anſwers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are your Thoughts as to Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by Chriſt's imputed Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I look only to be juſtified by Chriſt's Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs received by Faith.</p>
            <p>Being ask'd, <hi>What Evidence he had for Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſaid, he had good grounds of Hope many Years ago concerning his State of Grace: tho be was full of defects, yet the Merits of
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:63794:7"/> Chriſt were alſufficient, on which he truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Are you ſatisfied that you have delivered in your Sermons nothing but ſuch Goſpel-Truths, as you can own at the Tribunal of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Excepting humane Frailty, ſo far as I can remember I have never delivered any thing to my Hearers but what I dare die with, and go with to Judgment.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>H.</hi> continued, <hi>Whether have you any comfortable Seals of your Miniſtry?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He anſwered, I bleſs God I have, and have had more Fruits appearing ſince my Lying down, than I knew of before, eſpecially many young Perſons have appeared hopeful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are your Thoughts now as to your Non-conformity? Do you repent of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I bleſs God I am abundantly ſatisfied with it, and if I was to make my choice over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and if it were poſſible for me to ſee all the Sufferings which I have undergone for it, (which are nothing to what many of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Servants of God have ſuffered) and if they were all laid together, I would make the ſame Choice which I have made, and take my Non-conformity with them; and I bleſs God that I never ſo much as tampered with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What Legacies have you to leave?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:63794:8"/>I am unfit to give Counſel to you my Brother, but the words of the Apoſtle I leave with you, <hi>Be not weary of Well-doing, and you ſhall reap in due Time if you faint not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the latter end of his Sickneſs, it pleaſed his Heavenly Father to viſit him with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of painful Diſtempers, under all the Tortures of which he yet glorified God with great Patience, and expreſſed his Hope of his future Bleſſedneſs, ſaying, I am not ſick unto Death, but unto Eternal Life. He would often ſay, In a little while all will be well. As to the Eſtate and Condition of his Soul, he expreſſed himſelf to ſome Friends thus; I can now look back upon my Way and Work in the Miniſtry, and ſay, I have been Faithful; and I can look within, and ſay I have Peace; but after all, the bottom I would fix on is Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs, I would make him all in all.</p>
            <p>When his Body was brought exceeding low, yet he would be left alone ſometimes in the Day, (as was concluded) that he might with leſs diſtraction enjoy Communion with God in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Prayer and Meditation.</p>
            <p>A little before he died, ſome of his Hearers coming to him, and inquiring of him how he did? he ſaid, I long after your Spiritual and Soul-Welfare.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="xv" facs="tcp:63794:8"/>He departed this Life the <hi>18th</hi> of
<hi>June 1695.</hi> about eight of the Clock in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in the
<hi>70th</hi> Year of his Age. His pious Soul, which through the whole Courſe of his Life had been bent towards God, did ſhew her readineſs and preparedneſs for the full and eternal Fruition, by the ſweet and ardent Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things which it had that Night and Morning after him, which were often expreſſed in theſe words, Father, come and take me Home to thy ſelf.</p>
            <p>His Body was interred in <hi>Bury</hi> Church-Yard (being the Pariſh Church where he lived) cloſe by the Chancel-Wall, on the South ſide, <hi>June 20. Anno Dom. 1695.</hi> A vaſt Concourſe of People appeared at the Funeral, and made great Lamentation over him; the Reverend Mr.
<hi>Robert Seddon</hi> of <hi>Bolton,</hi> preached the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sermon at Mr.
<hi>Pendlebury</hi>'s own Chappel. The Subject of his Diſcourſe was in the
<hi>12th</hi> of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>13th</hi> Verſe, <hi>But go thou thy way till the End be; for thou ſhalt reſt and ſtand in thy Lot at the end of the Days.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have we ſorrowfully brought to the Grave this excellent Miniſter of Chriſt, who was truly <hi>a Nathaniel, an Iſraelite indeed,</hi> a Gracious, Humble, Meek-ſpirited Chriſtian, that lived as he preached, and preached as he believed: his exact Life was an accurate Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on his Doctrine; his Doctrine was ſound <pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:63794:9"/> and Scriptural; he was a ſolid, judicious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, that throughly ſtudied what he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: he was not forward in ſpeaking, but what was wanting in Number was made up in Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſneſs of words, they had all their full weight. He was beloved of all, and reverenced eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by Brethren in the Miniſtry, and his People whom he laboured and ſpent himſelf for about <hi>44</hi> Years, who will be ready to ſay of his Worth, what the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> ſaid of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Wiſdom, <hi>That the one half thereof is not here publiſh'd to the World.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63794:9"/>Inviſible Realities the Real Chriſtians greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment.</head>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <head>SERMON I.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 4.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q> While we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen; for the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE bleſſed Apoſtle having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the great Sufferings and grievous Perſecutions which the <hi>Corinthians</hi> had endured, and were enduring for the Goſpel's ſake, in the 8, 9, 10, 11 Verſes of this Chapter, proceeds in the following Verſes to annex the Grounds of their Patience, Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Conſtancy, and Conſolation, in all the Preſſures they went under. And theſe <pb n="2" facs="tcp:63794:10"/> may be reduced to two Heads; two things bore them up, and bore them out under all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> A certain Hope and Expectation of a glorious Reſurrection to Everlaſting Life, after all the ignominious Sufferings of this Life, <hi>Ver.</hi> 13, 14. <hi>We having the ſame Spirit of Faith, according as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, I believed, and therefore have I ſpoken: we alſo believe, and therefore ſpeak; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he which raiſed up the Lord Jeſus, ſhall raiſe up us alſo by Jeſus, and ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent us with you.</hi> As if he had ſaid, this is our Corroboration and our Conſolation, the Aſſurance that we have of a happy Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, by this we are kept from ſinking under Diſcouragements, while <hi>we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way delivered unto Death,</hi> Ver. 11.</p>
            <p>The 15th Verſe contains a Reaſon of his Confidence, of being the Companion of the believing <hi>Corinthians,</hi> after his many Sufferings, for as much as they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured for their Good, and the Glory of God; <hi>For all things are for your ſakes, that the abundant Grace might, through the Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving of many, redound to the Glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the firſt Ground of the Apoſtle's Conſtancy and Comfort, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. <hi>For which Cauſe we faint not; but though our outward Man periſh, yet the inward Man is renewed day by day; i. e.</hi> upon the confident Hope of Eternal Life we faint not, knowing this, <hi>that he which hath raiſed up the Lord Jeſus, ſhall raiſe up us alſo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63794:10"/>2. The Perſwaſion and Aſſurance they were ſettled in, that they ſhould not be loſers by the Sufferings and Afflictions which they were enduring: But that they ſhould all tend and turn, (1.) To their preſent Good; (2.) To their future Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To their preſent Good. <hi>Though our outward Man periſh,</hi> that is, we faint not for this Cauſe, as knowing that while our Bodies, with all thoſe things that tend to the maintaining and adorning of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Life, as Health, and Wealth, and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, fall into decay and moulder away, by the various Tribulations we are cruſhed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; yet our inward Man (to wit) our Souls, or our ſpiritual Eſtate, is renewed,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is made new again day by day, is daily reſtored more and more to its primitive Form and Beauty. So that we are not loſers, but gainers by our Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; if we loſe our Externals, loſe our Health, and loſe our Strength, and loſe our Peace, and loſe our Liberty, and loſe our Livelyhood, yet all this loſs is not without a Compenſation, we have it made up, we have it recompenſed with Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and things of Eternal Concernment: Our outward Loſſes are recompenſed with inward Gain, the decay of our temporal Good compenſated with the augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſpiritual Grace; while the things of Earth are going from us, the things of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63794:11"/> Heaven come into the room of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To their future Glory, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. as they were tending to their preſent Good, ſo they turned to their future Glory:
<hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>For our light Affliction which is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory.</hi> Here the Apoſtle ſhows,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What their Afflictions were now; 1. They were light; 2. Short.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What they wrought. Now theſe light and ſhort Afflictions, which are but for a moment, work for us, 1. Glory; 2. A weight of Glory; 3. An exceeding weight of Glory; 4. A far more exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weight of Glory; 5. A far more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and eternal weight of Glory. So that here is a threefold moſt excellent An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titheſis. I ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. For Affliction here is Glory, future Glory for preſent Affliction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For light Affliction, here is a weight <hi>(magnitudo)</hi> of Glory; not only ſo, but an exceeding weight, a far more exceeding weight of Glory. Weigh Afflictions, the weightieſt Afflictions, all the Afflictions of a Chriſtian with Glory, and there will be no proportion betwixt them; Rom.
8.18. <hi>For I reckon, that the Sufferings of this preſent Time are not worthy to be compared with the Glory which ſhall be revealed in us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. For ſhort Afflictions, Afflictions for a moment, here is eternal Glory, an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63794:11"/> weight of Glory. This is the other Ground of their Patience, Confidence and Conſolation: And now upon this the Words I have read come in, <hi>While we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen: for the things which are ſeen are temporal; but the things which are not ſeen, are eternal.</hi> In the whole Verſe you may take notice of two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How they came to make this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Afflictions, to reckon of them as light and ſhort: This was by looking; our Affliction is light, while we look at things not ſeen.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Why this looking made them thus to account, this was the vaſt Difference which they hereby diſcover'd to be between the preſent Affliction and future Glory: <hi>For the things which are ſeen, are temporal; but the things which are not ſeen, are eternal; i. e.</hi> Our preſent Afflictions and Sufferings, which are ſeen things, are Temporal, for a ſhort time, of ſhort continuance; but our future Glory and Happineſs, which are unſeen things, are endleſs and eternal.</p>
            <p>The Words may be conſidered, either, 1. Relatively, as they refer and have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Context; and ſo they carry in them an Account of the Way and Means whereby they came to this ſtability under their Afflictions, <hi>viz.</hi> by eying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things. Or,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63794:12"/>2. Abſolutely in themſelves, and ſo they carry in them an Account of their Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and Practice; or ſhew what it was they made their great Buſineſs in the World, <hi>viz.</hi> to eye and mind eternal unſeen things. I ſhall look on them at this time under the latter Conſideration; and ſo you have in them, </p>
            <p n="2">1. An Act expreſſed, <hi>we look,</hi> looking.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Object deſcribed: And this is done,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Negatively; We look not <hi>at things ſeen, Res hujus ſeculi,</hi> the Matters of this preſent Life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Affirmatively; We <hi>look at things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen, Res futuri ſeculi,</hi> at the things of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, and within the Vail; theſe are our Object, Scope and Aim, to theſe we look. But how could they look at things not ſeen? <hi>Oculus fidei longius penetrat quam omnes humanae naturae ſenſus: &amp; fides etiam ideo vocatur rerum inviſibilium Aſpectus.</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin. <hi>in locum.</hi> By the Eye of Faith they might look at them.</p>
            <p>There are ſeveral things very obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the words; I ſhall only at this time obſerve this from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> It is the great Part and Duty of Chriſtians in this Life, to look at things which are not ſeen: <hi>Or,</hi> it is the great Concern of Chriſtians to be looking at unſeen things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63794:12"/>In this we ſhall,</p>
            <p>Firſt prove, that there are unſeen things, things which are not ſeen, which are, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not viſible, don't appear to Eyes of Fleſh.</p>
            <p>And this will be evident from theſe five or ſix things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. From general Aſſertions in Scripture, that hold out to us a Being of things which are not ſeen, do not appear; ſee for this
<hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Faith is the Subſtance of things hoped for, and the Evidence of things not ſeen. Fide convincimur ad credenda quae non vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, perinde ac ſi manifeſtò in luce videren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Faith is an infallible Argument, a clear Conviction, a convincing Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Exiſtence, Reality and Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, that they are no Figments and Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but Realities. So then you ſee hence, that there are unſeen things;
<hi>Quae mente noſtrâ cernimus haud ſecus ac ſi praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia eſſent;</hi> Things which thrò Faith we ſee with our Minds as if they were preſent.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24. <hi>We are ſaved by Hope: but Hope that is ſeen, is not Hope: for what a Man ſeeth, why doth he yet hope for?</hi> As the antecedent and conſequent words ſhew, it is as if the Apoſtle had ſaid, We have a certain Apprehenſion of Redemption, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and final Freedom from all Calamities here, in Hope and Expectation, not in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Poſſeſſion; <hi>for Hope that is ſeen, is not Hope; i. e.</hi> if we had them in hand, we <pb n="8" facs="tcp:63794:13"/> could not be ſaid to hope for them: So that here again you ſee, there are unſeen things, the things of Hope; the things that Hope waits for are unſeen; Ver. 25. <hi>We hope for that we ſee not.</hi> Hence Believers are ſaid to have their Hope laid up for them in Heaven; <hi>Col.</hi> 1.5. <hi>For the Hope which is laid up for you in Heaven;</hi> the Subſtance of which things is Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.4. <hi>For ſince the beginning of the World Men have not heard, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Ear, neither hath the Eye ſeen, O God, beſides thee, what he hath prepared for him that waiteth for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark, (1.) Here are things prepared. (2.) Theſe prepared things are unknown things, Ear hath not heard them, Eye hath not ſeen them. (3.) They have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known things from the beginning.</p>
            <p>The Ear of Man hath heard of many things, and the Eye of Man hath ſeen many things up and down the World, in thoſe many Ages that the World hath ſtood; yet behind all theſe things, that ſo many thouſands and millions of Ears (now ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the Grave) have heard, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Eyes (now ſunk down in their Holes) have ſeen; I ſay, behind all theſe there are things that Ear hath never heard, that Eye hath never ſeen; that Time, which unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers many things, has not uncovered, in its manifold Revolutions, ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. It may appear there are unſeen things,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:63794:13"/>2. From the particular Enumerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which we have in the Scripture, of things which have not been ſeen, or are unſeen.</p>
            <p>The Holy Ghoſt mentions many things in particular that are
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, do not appear. As in a word only to inſtance in a few things.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The Holy Ghoſt makes report to us of a Life of Saints that is hid; <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Your-Life is hid with Chriſt in God;</hi> not only the Life of Grace, but eſpecially the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of that Life, the Life of Glory, this is hid.</p>
            <p>Hiding implies two things; 1. Safety; that the thing is in ſafety; ſo is this Life, for it's hid with Chriſt in God. 2. Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy; that the thing hid is covered and out of ſight; ſuch is the Life of Glory, it is a hidden Life, the Glory of it is cover'd, and out of the ſight of all Mortals.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) We read of manifeſtation of Sons; Rom. 8.19. <hi>For the earneſt Expectation of the Creature, waiteth for the manifeſtation of the Sons of God.</hi> And alſo to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, in 1 <hi>John</hi>
3.2. <hi>It doth not yet appear what we ſhall be.</hi> In both theſe places we have a Diſcovery that is to be made of the Sons of God. Behind all that is yet mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, or doth yet appear, there is a Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the Sons of God, it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be. O Sirs, the Sons of God ſhall be manifeſted with, and <pb n="10" facs="tcp:63794:14"/> appear in much Glory, much internal Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in their Souls and Bodies, much exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glory in their Privileges and Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that is not yet manifeſt, neither doth yet appear.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Glory to be revealed; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi>
5.1. <hi>And alſo a Partaker of the Glory that ſhall be revealed.</hi> Here is a Glory to be revealed, to be opened and uncovered, that is yet covered and unſeen; a Glory to be thus revealed in us, or among us, us who are now ſuffering among Men.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Wrath to come on Sinners; 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10.
<hi>Matth.</hi> 3.7. <hi>O Generation of Vipers, who hath warned you to flee from the Wrath to come?</hi> Wrath to come in another World, and in an eternal Eſtate, beſides and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind all that comes, and is ſeen in this World and preſent Time.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) Second Death, that poor Creatures (dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins) have to paſs under, when through the Door of the firſt Death. Rev. 2.11. <hi>He that overcometh, ſhall not be hurt of the ſecond Death.</hi> Rev. 20.6. <hi>Bleſſed and Holy is he that hath part in the firſt Reſurrection; on him the ſecond Death ſhall have no Power.</hi> There is then you ſee ſuch a thing as a ſecond Death. O think on it, poor Sinners, it's an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen thing, but an unqueſtionable thing; there is ſuch a thing certainly, and it's a dreadful thing: the firſt Death is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, the breadth of it is but a ſtep, the <pb n="11" facs="tcp:63794:14"/> length of it is but a moment of Time, or two; but the ſecond Death is ſomething, there are the Chambers of Death, where you ſhall be led from one Miſery to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and where you ſhall dwell for ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Being of unſeen things is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt from the ſpecial Diſtribution, or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, that the Scripture makes of things, into two ranks or ſorts. This is another thing that will yet put this Truth out of queſtion. We find the Holy Ghoſt diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting things,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Into things preſent and to come; Rom. 8.38. <hi>For I am perſwaded that neither Death, nor Life, nor Angels, nor Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor Powers, or things preſent, or things to come,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 3.22. there again you read of things preſent and to come.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Into thoſe of this Life, and of the Life to come; 1 Tim. 4.8. <hi>Godlineſs hath the Promiſe of the Life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Into things of this World, and that to come; Luke 20.34,
35. <hi>The Children of this World marry, and are given in Marriage; But they which ſhall be accounted worthy to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that World, and the Reſurrection from the Dead,</hi> &amp;c. Eph. 1.21. <hi>Every Name that is named, not only in this World, but in that which is to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Into things Above, and things on Earth; Col. 3.2. <hi>Set your Affections on things above, not on things on the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:63794:15"/>(5.) Things in Heaven and in Earth; Col.
1.16. <hi>For by him were all things created that are in Heaven, and that are in Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">(6.) Things Temporal and things Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; 2 Cor. 4.18. <hi>The things which are ſeen are Temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are Eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">(7.) Things Viſible and Inviſible; Col. 1.16. <hi>For by him were all things Created, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and inviſible;</hi> i. e. all the Creatures, for they are all viſible or inviſible; and as there are viſible, ſo there are inviſible unſeen Creatures. Thus things are diſtinguiſhed, into things preſent and to come. Now the things preſent, the things of this Life are viſible, are ſeen things; and the things to come, the things of the other Life are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, inviſible and unſeen.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Being of unſeen things is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the Examples or Experience of thoſe that have been brought within ſome ſight of unſeen things; thus <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> had a Praeludium, a Prefigurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the unſeen Glory of Heaven, in Chriſt's Transfiguration, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. So <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> when dying, <hi>ſaw the Glory of God, and Jeſus ſtanding on the right Hand of God,</hi> Acts
7.55. Mark, he ſaw into Heaven, and beheld Chriſt there in his Glory. If any would enquire here, <hi>de modo,</hi> how the Heavens were opened, and how he ſaw the Glory; it's both beſide my preſent Work, and above my Ability to ſatisfy <pb n="13" facs="tcp:63794:15"/> their Curioſity. <hi>Res patet, modus latet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that he was caught up into the third Heaven, into Paradiſe, the Place of God's Glory, the Habitation of Saints and Angels; and that there he heard wordleſs words, things impoſſible to be uttered, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2, 3, 4. Mark pray, he tells us again and again,
<hi>whether out of the Body, or in the Body, I can't tell, God knoweth;</hi> but this he can tell, that he was in the third Heaven, in Paradiſe, and heard unſpeakable words. So on the other ſide, as <hi>Stephen</hi> a little before his Death, had a foreſight of the unſeen Glory above, and dying, went into the full Poſſeſſion of it: ſo <hi>Judas</hi> a little before his Death had a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſte of the Woe and Worm below, and dying went to the full Experience of it; Acts 1.25. <hi>From which</hi> Judas <hi>by Tranſgreſſion fell, that he might go to his own place.</hi> So the
<hi>Sodomites</hi> are ſet out, <hi>Jude</hi> 7. not only for an Example of Admonition, to warn other Sinners, but as an Example of Conviction, to convince other Sinners that there is an eternal Fire; or for an Example of this Truth, that there are Sufferings not ſeen; remaining for impenitent and ſecure Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as thoſe that hear theſe words ſhall ſee and find one day, if Repentance and Grace prevent not.</p>
            <p n="5">5. From Scripture-Viſions, wherein the Lord hath made clear diſcoveries, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible repreſentations of inviſible things,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63794:16"/> things not ſeen, unto his Servants. The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen Judgment to come, was thus ſeen by <hi>Daniel</hi> in a Viſion; Dan. 7.9,
10. <hi>I beheld till the Thrones were caſt down, and the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of days did ſit, whoſe Garment was white as Snow, and the Hair of his Head like the pure Wooll: his Throne was like the fiery Flame, and his Wheels as burning Fire.</hi> Verſe 10. <hi>A fiery Stream iſſued and came forth from before him: thouſand thouſands miniſtred unto him, and ten thouſand times ten thouſand ſtood before him: the Judgment was ſet, and the Books were opened.</hi> By <hi>John</hi> in another Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Rev. 20.11, 12, 13. <hi>And I ſaw a great white Throne, and him that ſat on it, from whoſe Face the Earth and the Heaven fled away, and there was found no place for them.</hi> Ver. 12. <hi>And I ſaw the Dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before God, and the Books were opened; and another Book was opened, which is the Book of Life, and the Dead were judged out of thoſe things which were written in the Books, according to their Works.</hi> Ver. 13. <hi>And the Sea gave up the Dead which were in it; and Death and Hell delivered up the Dead which were in them, and they were judged every Man according to their Works.</hi> The triumphant Church was ſeen, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. That there be unſeen things, may be proved from the very Confeſſions of Pagans and Heathens; thoſe who have not had the Light of the Word, have yet had ſome confuſed, obſcure, and imperfect Apprehenſions of unſeen things, or that <pb n="15" facs="tcp:63794:16"/> there are inviſible things. Saith <hi>Plato, Exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat lex de hominibus ſub Saturno, &amp; ſemper &amp; nunc etiam extat apud Deos; &amp; quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> homines juſte pié<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vitam egiſſent, cum è vita migrarent, ad beatorum inſulas profecti, in omni foelicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te viverent, à malis longe ſejuncti: qui vero injuſte impié<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vixiſſent, in punitionis juſti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſupplicii carcerem quod appellant Tartarum i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent:</hi> in Gorgia, <hi>pag.</hi> 356. <hi>Qui ob ſcelerum magnitudinem inſanabiles eſſe videntur, hos omnis conveniens ſors mergit in Tartarum, unde nunquam egrediuntur.</hi> Idem <hi>in Phaedone,</hi> pag.
84.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Socrates</hi> rejoiced that he was to die, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſhould then go to ſee <hi>Homer, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiod,</hi> and other Worthies that were gone before.</p>
            <p>Yea, <hi>Bion</hi> of <hi>Boriſtenes</hi> the Atheiſt, who all his Life time had denied the Gods, and derided their Worſhip, yet when Death came was extreamly afraid of dying, and that not ſo much becauſe of the loſs of Life, or Pains of Death, but for fear of what followed after Death.</p>
            <p>I might much enlarge here: from this Principle thoſe things took their Riſe that we find either in Poets or Philoſophers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Elyſian Fields, the Stygean Lake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe Arguments we may ſee that there are unſeen things. The next Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry we ſhall make is,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:63794:17"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> What theſe things are which are not ſeen, and which Chriſtians are to look at.</p>
            <p>Now the Holy Scripture (which muſt be our Guide in this Enquiry) brings us ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of many things, that to us and all the Living are not ſeen, do not appear. I ſhall at this Time confine my ſelf to, and ſum up all I ſhall ſay as to this in four Heads; there are theſe four things which are not ſeen, and that it concerns us to look at.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Death, 2. Judgment, 3. Heaven, 4. Hell.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The things of Death are unſeen things, things not ſeen: as in a word,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The time of Death is unſeen. <hi>The Living know that they ſhall die,</hi> Eccl. 9.5. but they know not when they ſhall die. Gen.
27.2. <hi>I know not the Day of my Death:</hi> So thou and I may ſay, I know not the Hour, Day, Week, Month, Year, wherein Death will come, it's unſeen. When an Hour is paſt, or a Day over, we may ſay that was not the Day or Hour; but we cannot ſay of the Day or Hour which is yet to come, that it ſhall not be the Time. Prov. 27.1. <hi>Boaſt not thy ſelf of to morrow, for thou knoweſt not what a Day may bring forth:</hi> the Day thou art now in, and ſpending on, may bring forth unſeen Death. The time of Death is one thing unſeen, this is one, no Man knows when it will be, at what Day, in what Year it will come, whether in Youth, or in old <pb n="17" facs="tcp:63794:17"/> Age. O think on this, Sirs, the Time will come when you muſt die; but when this will be, is covered from you, you ſee it not, it may be at any Inſtant, in any Moment. Mark 13.35. <hi>Watch ye therefore, for ye know not when the Maſter of the Houſe cometh, at Even, or at Midnight, or at the Cock crowing, or in the Morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The Place of Death is unſeen; this is another. As we ſee not when, ſo we ſee not where we muſt die, in what Place, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at Home, or Abroad, in the Houſe, or in the Field, in the Bed, or at the Board. It may be thou haſt been ſhewed where it was that thou waſt born, in what Place thou cameſt into the World and took thy firſt Breath; ay but they that have ſhewed thee this, cannot take thee again by the Hand, and lead thee to ſee the Place where thou muſt take thy laſt Breath and die, and go out of this World into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; this is unſeen, thou cannot ſay, lo it is here, or lo there it is; or if thou wilt, yet it may be neither here nor there, but ſomewhere elſe that thou never thinkſt of.</p>
            <p>It's ſaid of <hi>Eſchilus</hi> the Poet in <hi>Sicily,</hi> that on a Day walking out of the Town where he dwelt to take the Air, he ſate him down upon a high Place, and having his Head (being bald) bare and uncovered, an Eagle flew over him in the Air, with a Tortoiſe in her Talons, and ſeeing his white Head, took it for a Stone, and ſo let <pb n="18" facs="tcp:63794:18"/> it fall from a great Height thereon to break the Tortoiſe-ſhell, which broke his Scull, whereof he died preſently. One would have thought that this could not have been the Place of ſuch a Death, but rather that it was impoſſible for any thing to fall on his Head, unleſs the Heavens themſelves had dropt down: but alas, Death can come on us any where, we are no where out of its reach, neither know we where it will meet us; when we think our ſelves moſt ſafe, or never think of it, it may thus drop on our Heads. When
<hi>Bibu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> the Roman General was riding in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in all his Glory through the Streets of <hi>Rome,</hi> a Tile fell from a Houſe and beat out his Brains. Many have ſeen Death where they have never thought of ſeeing it, and thou knoweſt not where thou may'ſt ſee it. Pſal. 89.48.
<hi>What Man is he that liveth and ſhall not ſee Death?</hi> That's the Pſalmiſt's Queſtion, it may be mine, What Man is he that lives (of you that are here to day) that can tell, where it is he muſt ſee Death? which he cannot ſcape ſeeing ſomewhere; and it's a Queſtion you can none of you anſwer. O that you would think of it, and labour to be ſuch, as you may be ready to ſee it in any Place.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) The manner of Death is unſeen: as we ſee not when or where, ſo we can as little ſee how we muſt die, by what kind or manner of Death we muſt go out of <pb n="19" facs="tcp:63794:18"/> this World: there is but one way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the World, one Door that we all came in at at our Entrance, but there are many ways out of the World. <hi>Mors eſt bellua Centiceps,</hi> and comes a hundred ways. The Jews reckon 903 kinds of Death; but among all the kinds that we may obſerve, we can't ſee our own ſo as to ſingle it out, and ſay, by this kind of Death I ſhall go into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World; this is covered from the Eyes of all Fleſh. <hi>Jacob</hi> died in his Bed;
<hi>Joſiah</hi> by the Sword; <hi>Job</hi>'s Children by the fall of the Houſe where they were eating; <hi>Eli</hi> by a fall from the Seat where he was ſitting: Death began with <hi>Aſa</hi> in his Feet, and ſtruck him there e're it came to ſtrike him at the Heart, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.12. Death begun with the Murmuring <hi>Iſraelites</hi> at the Heart, and ſtruck them with their Meat in their Mouths, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.33. We ſee daily ſome die a natural, others a violent Death; ſome by this, ſome by that, and ſome by the other kind of Sickneſs: ſome go out of the World by a Death that gives them long Warning, others ſhort Warning, and others none at all; and in this reſpect (I ſay) Death is an unſeen thing with you and me, we know not which of the many kinds of it, whether this or that, or the other, is a coming to let us into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.8. there we have Death riding on his pale Horſe, deſcribed in the 7th <hi>verſe,</hi> we may ſee whence he came, <hi>And when he had opened the fourth Seal, I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63794:19"/> heard the Voice of the fourth Beaſt ſay, Come and ſee: and I looked, and behold, a Pale Horſe, and his Name that ſate on him was Death.</hi> Mark, he came from under a Seal, broke out upon the opening of a Seal. Death is ſealed, thy Death and my Death are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining under the Seal of the Everliving God, concealed from thee and me and all Mortals, and not to be known till he open the Seal and ſend them out. Death, I ſay, is ſealed; and as no Man knows what is in a Letter till the Seal be opened, ſo no more do we know at what Time, or in what Place, or by what manner of Death we muſt go out of this World, before the Lord break open the Seal, and ſend Death on Horſeback to our Doors.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) I might add the nature of Death is unſeen; we hear much of the Name, but alas we ſee little of the Nature of Death: we are acquainted with the word Death, O but we have little Acquaintance with the work or thing,
<hi>Death:</hi> now we talk of it, and diſcourſe of it at a diſtance, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, Sirs, when that which is called ſeeing Death, and taſting Death, meets us, Death will be another thing than now it's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly taken to be with many. Deut. 32.29. <hi>O that they were wiſe, that they underſtood this, that they would conſider their latter End.</hi> Well this is the firſt; Death, as I told you in the entrance on the Particulars, is the Door, the Way, to things which are not <pb n="21" facs="tcp:63794:19"/> ſeen; and I tell you here again in the cloſe of it, that this Door to things unſeen, is alſo unſeen. Pray think of it you that are here to day; 1. You believe you muſt die. 2. This thing that you call dying or Death, is I tell you a Door, an Inlet to unſeen things, things behind all that have ever been ſeen in the World. 3. This Death that is thus a Door to thoſe unſeen things, is it ſelf an unſeen thing; the Time of it is unſeen, and the Place of it is unſeen, and the Kind of it is unſeen: you know nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when, nor where, nor how it will come upon any of you. Therefore cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, Sirs, it concerns you to look at this, and to look how you are provided to meet this unſeen thing, that is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of unſeen things; Unſeen Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is next behind this, an unſeen Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or Hell, Salvation or Damnation is next behind that; you know not when or where you may ſee Death, but as ſoon as ever you have ſeen Death, you muſt ſee Judgment; and as ſoon as ever you have ſeen Judgment, you muſt ſee Heaven or Hell for ever. I pray you think of it; art thou not a Drunkard? why the next Time thou goeſt to the Ale-houſe thou mayſt ſee Death there, and ſo never ſee Houſe more, but Hell-houſe. Art thou a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator, or Adulterer? Art thou a Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? art thou a Profaner of the Lord's Day? O remember Death that is now <pb n="22" facs="tcp:63794:20"/> unſeen may ſurprize thee in the very act of thy Sin, this is the Porch and Door to the unſeen things of another World, and it's alſo an unſeen thing, a thing not ſeen, that leads to things not ſeen, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible thing that is an Introduction to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible things, that are Eternal; the things of Death I ſay are unſeen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:63794:20"/>
            <head>SERMON II.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 4.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q> While we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen; for the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>SEcondly,</hi> The things of the great Day of Judgment are unſeen things, things which are not ſeen. There ſhall be ſuch a Day as this, a general Judgment of all Men; Acts 17.31. <hi>Becauſe he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a Day in which he will judg the World in Righteouſneſs, by that Man whom he hath ordained; whereof he hath given Aſſurance unto all Men, in that he hath raiſed him from the Dead.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.10. <hi>For we muſt all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his Body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad.</hi> Mat. 12.36. <hi>but I ſay unto you, That every idle word that Men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall give Account thereof in the Day of Judgment.</hi> There ſhall then be ſuch a Day, a Day of Judgment; and I ſay, the <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63794:21"/> things of that Day are unſeen, are things which do not appear, therefore it is called the Day of Revelation; Rom. 2.5.
<hi>But after thy hardneſs and impenitent Heart, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureſt up unto thy ſelf Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath, and Revelation of the righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Patefactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> the Day of the Manifeſtation of the righteous Judgment of God; in this Day the righteous Judgment of God ſhall be fully manifeſted, and appear to all Men in this World. Eccleſ. 8.14. <hi>There be Juſt Men unto whom it happeneth according to the work of the Wicked: again, there be wicked Men to whom it happeneth according to the work of the Righteous.</hi> And upon this the Juſtice and Equity of God is oft-times queſtioned, and accuſed, by the Raſh and Prepoſterous Judgment of Men; Good Men are apt to think they have hard Meaſure, and ill Men are ready to think that God is ſuch a one as themſelves; but there ſhall be ſuch a Revelation of the righteous Judgment of God, as ſhall ſet all Matters and Men too to Rights, and it ſhall appear to all that the Judgment of God is Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, <hi>and the Heavens ſhall declare his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; for God is Judg himſelf,</hi> Pſal. 50.6. i. e. (as <hi>Diod.</hi>) God's Juſtice ſhall in this Judgment of his be manifeſted to all the World, as plainly as thoſe things which from Heaven are ſeen here upon Earth.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:63794:21"/>
               <l>And when theſe things are tried,</l>
               <l>The Heavens ſhall record</l>
               <l>That God is Juſt, and all muſt bide</l>
               <l>The Judgment of the Lord.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It will be, I ſay, a Day of Revelation, <hi>Ambae civitates (terrena &amp; coeleſtis) tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralibus vel bonis pariter utuntur, vel malis pariter affliguntur, donec ultimo Juditio ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur, &amp; percipiat unaequaeque ſuum finem, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus nullus eſt finis.</hi> Aug. <hi>De Civit Dei, Lib.</hi> 18. <hi>Cap.</hi> 54. O the righteous Judgment of God ſhall be ſeen as clear as the Light at Noon-day, in that Day: So this Day is in Scripture called,
<list>
                  <item>1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
               </list> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <list>
                  <item>The Revelation</item>
                  <item>Appearing</item>
                  <item>Manifeſtation</item>
               </list> of Chriſt. </p>
            <p>All which Phraſes import a detection and uncovering of Chriſt in that Day, behind what has been or is ſeen in this Life: It will be (I ſay) the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt; 1 Cor. 1.7. <hi>Waiting for the Revelation of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1.7. <hi>The Lord ſhall be revealed from Heaven;</hi> 1 Pet. 1.7. <hi>At the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> ver. 13. <hi>At the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> The original word in all theſe Places, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies an opening, an uncovering, a draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Vail from over that that's covered, that it may be ſeen. Such will this Day be, <hi>detectio occultarum rerum Chriſti,</hi> an uncovering of his hidden Glory.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:63794:22"/>2. The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the appearing of Chriſt; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.14. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. The word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a bright or clear Appearing, or ſhining out; and it will be a glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the words are, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13.
<hi>the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Appearing of the Great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Manifeſtation of Chriſt; Col. 3.4. 1 Pet. 5.4. 1 John 3.2. <hi>But we know that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> The Word imports an Illuſtration, a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation by clear Light, of ſomething hid in Darkneſs; Chriſt ſhall at this Day come as out of Darkneſs into Light. O Sirs, there will be thus a glorious Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a glorious Appearing, a glorious Manifeſtation of Chriſt in this Day, ſuch as was never ſeen in the World to this Day, nor ever ſhall be ſeen before that Day. Remember this, my Friends, there will be a great and notable Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the things of that Day are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things. There was a great Diſcovery of things at Chriſt's firſt coming in the Fleſh, that had been hid from Men of all Times and Ages, and kept unſeen till then; Rom. 16.25. <hi>According to the Revelation of the Myſtery which was kept ſecret ſince the World began;</hi> here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an opening of the Secret, that there had been Silence about, that there had been <pb n="27" facs="tcp:63794:22"/> nothing ſaid of in the World, from the beginning to that Day; So <hi>Col.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Even the Myſtery, which had been hid from Ages and Generations, but now is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to his Saints:</hi> here again we have a Myſtery which hath been,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a hidden Secret: Thus the Redemption of the World, the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were a Myſtery hid from Ages and Generations, and either not known at all as among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> or opened more obſcurely in the dark glaſs of Types, Shadows, Prophecies as to the Jews: but this great Myſtery thus covered from all, was opened and uncovered at his firſt Coming; and therefore, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.23, 24. ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Bleſſed are the Eyes that ſee the things that ye ſee. For I tell you, that many Prophets and Kings have deſired to ſee thoſe things which ye ſee, and have not ſeen them; and to hear thoſe things which ye hear, and have not heard them.</hi> 1 Tim. 3.16. <hi>God manifeſt in the Fleſh,</hi> the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Types, the fulfilling of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. And as there was thus a great ſeeing of things before unſeen, at the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt in the Fleſh, ſo there ſhall be a greater opening of things at Chriſt's ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Coming to Judgment, that have been hid from all Ages <hi>(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mundi initio)</hi> from the Beginning, are hid from the preſent Age, and that ſhall be hid from all following A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and not be ſeen till that Day, that Great <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63794:23"/> Day of the Lord reveal them. O, Sirs, the things which the Scripture reports unto us of this Day, are all to us unſeen things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I.
<list>
                     <item>1. The coming of Chriſt riding through the Clouds on his Chariot of Glory.</item>
                     <item>2. The thouſand thouſands of Angels that ſhall miniſter unto him.</item>
                     <item>3. The Multitude of Saints that he ſhall bring with him.</item>
                     <item>4. The Glory that he ſhall appear in, are things which are not ſeen.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>II.
<list>
                     <item>1. The great White Throne.</item>
                     <item>2. His ſitting upon the Throne of his Glory.</item>
                     <item>3. The ſounding of the Trumpet.</item>
                     <item>4. The opening of the Graves.</item>
                     <item>5. The riſing of the Dead in numberleſs numbers all the Earth over; <hi>When the Sea ſhall give up its Dead,</hi> Rev. 20.13. are things which are not ſeen.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>III.
<list>
                     <item>1. The gathering of all Nations, all Men that ever were, now are, or hereafter ſhall be, before him.</item>
                     <item>2. The ſeparation of the Sheep.</item>
                     <item>3. The Collocation, the placing of them.</item>
                     <item>4. The opening of the Books, that will lay open all the Thoughts, Words, and Works of all Men.</item>
                     <item>5. The ſtanding of the Dead both great and ſmall at the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63794:23"/>6. The Judging of the World in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</item>
                     <item>7. The Promulgation of the final Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</item>
                     <item>8. The Execution of it, in ſending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way one part with a
<hi>Go ye Curſed into everlaſting Fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels,</hi> in welcoming another part, with a <hi>Come ye Bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the Foundation of the World;</hi> are things which are not ſeen: O Sirs, theſe, theſe are unſeeen things.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>IV.
<list>
                     <item>1. The Wailings of Sinners, when they ſhall ſee the Lord Jeſus revealed in flaming Fire from Heaven.</item>
                     <item>2. The wringing of Hands when they ſhall ſee the Books opening before all the World.</item>
                     <item>3. The fearful Tremblings, when they ſhall hear themſelves doomed to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Burnings.</item>
                     <item>4. The dreadful Cries and horrible Noiſe of Wailings and Lamentations that they ſhall go away with, when they are going to the eternal Priſon, are unſeen things. We ſee enough and too much of the mad Mirth, and ringing Shouts of Profane Creatures now, when they are met about their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations: O but we ſee not how their Chear will change, the Cry, the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63794:24"/> Cry, the doleful Cry, that will be among this ſort of Perſons, in this great Day of Wrath, and Revelation of the righteous Judgment of God Almighty.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe things, Sirs, and many other things of this great Day, which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture tells us of, are to us things which are not ſeen. This is the ſecond thing, pray re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it, there ſhall be a Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and there are great things to be ſeen at that Day, which now are not ſeen, which ſhall not be ſeen till this Day appear and bring them into Sight: Saints ſhall ſee <hi>that</hi> they have never ſeen before; Sinners ſhall ſee <hi>that</hi> they have never ſeen before, all the World ſhall ſee that which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The things of Heaven are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things, things which are not ſeen; theſe are chiefly meant in the Text, by the things which are not ſeen, as both the antecedent and conſequent words ſhew; and theſe are unſeen things, I ſay, things within the Vail, as the Apoſtle's Phraſe is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19. an expreſſion uſed in Alluſion to the moſt Holy Place in the Tabernacle and Temple, wherein were the Ark of the Teſtimony, the Mercy-Seat, the two Tables, the Pot of Manna,
<hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod, the Golden Cenſor, before which there was a great Vail drawn, that none might ſee them, but only the <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63794:24"/> High Prieſt, who entred once a Year; Exod. 26.31. <hi>And thou ſhalt make a Vail of Blue, and Purple, and Scarlet, and fine twined Linen of cunning Work: with Cherubims ſhall it be made.</hi> In alluſion to this (I ſay) the things of Heaven are ſaid to be within the Vail, <hi>i. e.</hi> covered and unſeen. As there was a Vail between the People, and that which was in the moſt Holy Place, ſo there is a Vail between us, and that which is in Heaven.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The things in Heaven which are ſet down in Scripture by the Names; (1.) Of a better Countrey, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16. A Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey where there is no Hunger, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.16. no Death, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.4. no Night,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 21.25. no Curſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3. (2.) By the Name of Paradiſe, the Place where there is <hi>fulneſs of Joy, and Pleaſures for evermore,</hi> Pſal. 16.11. (3.) By Chriſt's Father's Houſe, John 14.2.
<hi>In my Father's Houſe are many Manſions.</hi> (4.) By a City which hath Foundations, whoſe Builder and Maker is God; a City whoſe Foundations are precious Stones, Gates Pearls, Streets pure Gold, Porters Angels, <hi>and that hath no need of the Sun, neither of the Moon to ſhine in it; for the Glory of God doth lighten it, and the Lamb is the Light thereof,</hi> Rev. 21.23. (5.) By <hi>an Inheritance, an Inheritance that is incorruptible, undefiled, and that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not away, reſerved in Heaven,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.4. (6.) By a Kingdom, a Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <pb n="32" facs="tcp:63794:25"/> a Kingdom of God, a Kingdom of Chriſt, a Kingdom that cannot be moved, a Kingdom that is Eternal, Everlaſting. (7.) By a Crown of Righteouſneſs, of Life, of Glory. (8.) By Glory, Heavenly Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, an exceeding and eternal Weight of Glory. I ſay, the things of Heaven ſet out by all theſe Names and Titles, are all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things.</p>
            <p>And ſo alſo, Secondly, the things which are ſhadowed out to us,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) By the World to come; (2.) The New Heavens; (3.) The New Earth; (4.) The Throne of God, and the Lamb; (5.) The Temple of God; (6.) The pure River of the Water of Life, clear as Chryſtal; (7.) The Tree of Life, which bears twelve manner of Fruits, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2. are unſeen things.</p>
            <p>And, Thirdly, the things ſet out,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) By ſitting down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and
<hi>Jacob,</hi> in the Kingdom of Heaven; (2.) By ſitting with Chriſt in his Throne, as he is ſet down with his Father in his Throne; (3.) By being called to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-Supper of the Lamb; (4.) By eating and drinking at his Table in his Kingdom; (5.) By eating the hidden Manna, are all hidden unſeen things.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we ſee not yet what it is,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) To ſee God; (2.) To ſee his Face; (3.) To ſee him face to face; (4.) To know as we are known; (5.) To be before the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63794:25"/> Throne of God; (6.) To have him that ſitteth on the Throne to dwell among us; (7.) To walk with him in White; (8.) To follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth; (9.) To have the Lamb which is in the midſt of the Throne to feed us, and to lead us unto living Fountains of Water; (10.) To be made Pillars in the Temple of God, and to have the Name of God, and the Name of the City of God, which is new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and Chriſt's new Name written upon us; (11.) To be ever with the Lord; (12.) To have him all in all: all theſe things are things which are moſt clearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to, and moſt ſurely believed among the Saints, but are not yet ſeen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, And ſo;</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The Life of Saints that's hid with Chriſt in God; (2.) The Hope of Saints that's laid up in Heaven; (3.) The Glory to be revealed in Saints in Heaven; and (4.) The Inheritance of all things, are yet out of ſight.</p>
            <p>O Chriſtians, (1.) You that are going for Heaven to Day, have not ſeen what a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, City, Kingdom, Company you are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, what things you are going to ſee. (2.) You that have ſeen ſomething of the workings of Grace in your Hearts from Heaven, have ſeen nothing of the Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Glory for you in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Theſe are things which Eye hath not ſeen. O be ſtedfaſt, be immoveable, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh <pb n="34" facs="tcp:63794:26"/> your Hearts until the Day break, and the Shadows fly away, the Day when all theſe unſeen things ſhall be ſeen and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for evermore: this Day will bring to light and into ſight more than our thoughts can at preſent reach.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The things of Hell are unſeen things, things which are not ſeen: as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo Hell is hidden from the Eyes and ſight of all the Living. The Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> denotes a place unſeen; and our Engliſh word Hell is from <hi>Hil,</hi> an old Saxon word, that ſignifies to be hid, hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led over or covered: ſuch is that Place, ſuch are the things of that Place, things which are hill d over, things which are not ſeen.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The things in Hell which are ſet out in Scripture by the Names of,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The ſecond Death; (2.) The bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Pit; (3.) Of Perdition; (4.) Of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; (5.) Of Damnation; (6.) Of the Wrath to come; and (7.) Of the Wine-preſs of the Wrath of God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are things which are not ſeen.</p>
            <p>Theſe dreadful Expreſſions are Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that carry in them Rivers of unſeen Woes, Seas of unſeen Vengeance; yea whole Oceans of unſeen and unutterable Torments.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The things ſhadowed out to us,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) By Darkneſs, outer Darkneſs, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Darkneſs; (2.) By Chains, Chains of everlaſting Darkneſs; (3.) By the Wine <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63794:26"/> of the Wrath of God; (4.) By a Worm, a Worm that ſhall never die; (5.) And by a Fire, a Fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels, a Furnace of Fire, a Lake of Fire, a Furnace and Lake of unquenchable and everlaſting Fire; I ſay, the things ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed out by all theſe to us, are unſeen things.</p>
            <p>O Sirs, you that live impenitently and ſecurely in Sin, that Scoff, and Swear, and Drink, and Whore, and profane the Lord's day, and make light of Threatnings, Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Admonitions, as if you had made a Covenant with Death, and were at an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with Hell, as they who ſaid,
<hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15. <hi>We have made a Covenant with Death, and with Hell are we at Agreement: when the overflowing Scourge ſhall paſs through, it ſhall not come unto us; for we have made Lies our Refuge, and under Falſhood have we hid our ſelves:</hi> that is, as if they had ſaid, Death and Hell are at amity with us, we fear no more harm from them than we do from thoſe that are in League with us, than we do from Confederates, we are at Agreement with Hell, Hell ſhall not hurt us: or as if they had ſaid, we are in no more fear of Hell, than we are in fear of our Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates; for Hell is but a Fable, a Bug-bear, to fright Children and Fools; let Preachers ſay what they will, we care not for Hell, either it is not, or it is not ſo terrible as they tell us. Are you of this Temper, Sirs? <pb n="36" facs="tcp:63794:27"/> do you live looſely and profanely, ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and careleſly in a ſinful State and Way, and yet ſay we have made a Covenant with Death, and are at an Agreement with Hell, we fear not Hell, we care not for Hell?</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Either it is not; Or (2.) we ſhall eſcape it; Or (3.) it will not prove ſo hot as we are told: why I ſay your Covenant with Death ſhall be diſannulled, and your Agreement with Hell ſhall not ſtand; you'l find there is a Hell, and this Hell will be what now you are told of.</p>
            <p>Alas, alas, you have not ſeen what it is, (1.) To be turned into Hell; (2.) To go into Perdition; (3.) To be puniſhed with everlaſting Deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord; (4.) To fall into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the Devil; (5.) To be thrown into the great Wine-preſs of the Wrath of God; (6.) To be caſt alive into the Lake of Fire, burning with Brimſtone; (7.) To be tormented Day and Night for ever and ever; (8.) To feel an endleſs Rain of Snares, Fire and Brimſtone, and a burning Tempeſt; (9.) To ſuffer the Vengeance of an Eternal Fire; (10.) And to have the Smoke of your Torment aſcend for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>You have not ſeen theſe I ſay, you ſee not what is lying in their Womb, but they will come in ſight; and know to day, that as light as you make of them, they will cauſe you change Chear for ever; <hi>Mat.</hi>
25.30. <pb n="37" facs="tcp:63794:27"/> 
               <hi>There ſhall be Weeping and Gnaſhing of Teeth:</hi> this is their Caſe who are now in outer Darkneſs; and tho you may laugh at it now, it will be your Caſe there, there's no laughing or jeſting in Hell, but only weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth. Pray think of it you that are going for Hell, you little think what a Place and Things you are going to, what you ſhall both ſee and feel there: the things thereof are things that are not ſeen; and it's not ſafe to make light of that you ſee not, nor good to praiſe Hell before you have try'd it, and wo to you if you come to try it once, for that once will be for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The third Queſtion under the Doctrine is, how theſe things are unſeen. You ſee there are unſeen things, and what theſe unſeen things are, the things of Death, Judgment, Heaven, and Hell. Now the next inquiry may be this, in order to the clearing of the Point,
<hi>(viz.) How they are unſeen,</hi> or what this imports or implies that they are not ſeen.</p>
            <p>Now this Phraſe implies theſe four or five things,
<hi>(viz.)</hi> That they are things which,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Are not ſeen with Eyes of Fleſh, they are not ſeen, that is, they are not viſible to our bodily Eyes, not beheld with the Eye that looks upon viſible Objects, and things under the Sun; Eye hath not ſeen them. My Beloved, your Eye hath ſeen a great Number, and a great variety of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, <pb n="38" facs="tcp:63794:28"/> you are not able to tell how many Things, and how many kinds of Things you have ſeen ſince you begun to look out at theſe Windows; but I can tell you what you have not ſeen: among all the Things which you have ſeen Day after Day, you have never ſeen the things of Death, the things of Judgment, the things of Heaven, nor the things of Hell, theſe have all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long been out of your ſight.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Haſt thou ſeen <hi>great</hi> Things, <hi>great</hi> Tranſactions, <hi>great</hi> Revolutions? thou haſt ſeen no ſuch
<hi>great</hi> Things, as the Things of the <hi>great</hi> Day of the Lord. (2.) Haſt thou ſeen <hi>good</hi> Things, Things that were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding amiable, lovely, and deſirable in thine Eye, that thine Eye was much taken with? yet thou haſt ſeen no ſuch <hi>good,</hi> love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and deſirable Things, as thoſe of Heaven and Glory are. (3.) Haſt thou ſeen
<hi>ill</hi> Things, Things that have been Dreadful, Terrible, Aſtoniſhing and Amazing to thee, that have frighted thee, that have put thee into a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation? why, yet for all that thou haſt ſeen no ſuch terrible or aſtoniſhing Things, as the things of Hell and Damnation: this is one, theſe things are not ſeen by the Eye of the Body.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It imports, that theſe unſeen things are n t known, they are not ſeen, that is, they are not fully known and underſtood by us: as they are things which are not ſeen by the Eye of Fleſh, ſo they are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63794:28"/> things which are not ſeen fully by the Eye of the Mind; the Eye ſees them not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the Mind reach them proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably to the Nature of them. Alas, it's but a little that we underſtand of theſe things, our Knowledg of them is mighty obſcure, dark, confuſed, and imperfect, as <hi>Job</hi> ſays of the Knowledg of God; Job 26.14. <hi>Lo, theſe are but parts of his Ways, and how little a Portion is heard of him? the Thunder of his Power who can underſtand?</hi> i. e. all that we hear and know, and conceive of God, is little, low, and nothing to what he is; all our Thoughts, Meditations, Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are infinitely below his infinite Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. So may I ſay of theſe unſeen Things, lo, theſe are part of them, theſe Things we have hinted at; but how little a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is heard of them? it's but little, very little, exceeding little, that we do or can conceive of unſeen Things to what they are, and what we ſhall find them to be. The <hi>Italians</hi> have a Proverb, <hi>Qui Venetias non videt non credit, &amp; qui aliquandiu ibi non vixit non intelligit.</hi> So it is in this Caſe, he that hath not ſeen theſe Things not ſeen, cannot believe enough of them; and he that hath not had ſome Experience of them, cannot underſtand them as they are.</p>
            <p>One of the Fathers branches things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three Heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Things that are known. 2. Things that are knowable, that may be found out <pb n="40" facs="tcp:63794:29"/> by Search and Enquiry. 3. Things that are neither known, nor knowable, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for another World: and of this ſort are theſe unſeen Things, they are not now known, or knowable, but the Knowledg of them is reſerved for another World. Alas, the Secrets of Nature are much above us, there are many thouſand Things there that we either have no Knowledg of, or know but very darkly; <hi>the Secrets of Grace are more above us, but the Secrets of Glory are moſt of all above us,</hi> the Knowledg of them is too wonderful for us, we cannot attain unto it. Says
<hi>Zophar,</hi> Job 11.7, 8, 9. <hi>Canſt thou by ſearching find out God? canſt thou find out the Almighty unto Perfection? It is as high as Heaven, what canſt thou do? deeper than Hell, what canſt thou know? The Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thereof is longer than the Earth, and broader than the Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's as high: What's as high? Why God's Perfection, this is as high. So may I ſay here, canſt thou find out unſeen Things by ſearching to Perfection; alas, no, no, they are as high as Heaven, what can we do? deep as Hell, what can we know?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> who was a Man of eminent Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, extraordinary Revelations, and ſtood on a higher riſe of Ground than any now living; yet tells us, that he ſaw but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>(modo imperfecto)</hi> in part, he ſaw but the back-parts of unſeen Things; 1 Cor. 13.9. <hi>We know in part, and propheſy <pb n="41" facs="tcp:63794:29"/> in part.</hi> Ver. 11. <hi>When I was a Child, I ſpake as a Child, I underſtood as a Child, I thought as a Child.</hi> He compares all the Knowledg he had attained of theſe Things, to that he had of things in the World when he was a Child. Children have but weak and ſhallow Conceptions and Apprehenſions of things, ſuch as they are aſhamed of, when they grow up to be Men. Why there is (in many reſpects) as great Difference between the Apprehenſions we have of unſeen Things now in this World, and the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions we ſhall have of the ſame Things in the other World, as there is between the Apprehenſions of Perſons whilſt but Children, and when come to be Men. Alas, Sirs, when you hear Men of the largeſt Abilities diſcourſing of theſe Things, they do but even liſp, and ſtammer, and ſpeak half words, and bits of Sentences, as Children; they do but talk of them as blind Men do of Colours, or as you do of far Countries, and Rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in them that you have never, never ſeen.</p>
            <p>O the things of Heaven are other things, and the things of Hell are other Things than you or I think, unknown Things! we ſee not (when our Conceptions are moſt accurate and elevated) a thouſandth thouſandth part of that Glory that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Saints in Heaven; nor yet a thouſandth thouſandth part of that Shame, <pb n="42" facs="tcp:63794:30"/> Wo, and Wrath, that is prepared for Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in Hell. Heaven is not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurate to our greateſt Hopes, but as far above them, as it is above the Earth; and Hell is not only anſwerable to our greateſt Fears, but as far beyond them as the Eaſt is from the Weſt. Says <hi>Moſes,</hi> Pſal. 90.11. <hi>Who knoweth the Power of thine Anger? ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy Fear, ſo is thy Wrath.</hi> That is, the Wrath of God is every way anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the Fear that Men have of it; and not only ſo, but it is behind what we either fear or can know. Think on this under the moſt dreadful Conſiderations ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable; and yet (when thou haſt thought the worſt, and all that is poſſible) accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy Fear, ſo is his Wrath, and more than ſo when poured out to the utmoſt. This is the ſecond, they are not ſeen, that is, not known.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are not experienced, they are not ſeen; that is, they are not try'd and felt by Experience, we have not had a trial of them by Taſte or Feeling. This Phraſe of ſeeing, is often put thus for feeling in Holy Scripture, as <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.1. <hi>I am the Man that hath ſeen Affliction by the Rod of his Wrath;</hi> as if he had ſaid, I have felt, endured, born Affliction. So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.15. <hi>The Years wherein we have ſeen Evil;</hi> ſuffer'd, felt Evil and Affliction. Jer. 20.18.
<hi>Wherefore came I forth out of the Womb to ſee Labour and Sorrow?</hi> Rev. 18.7. Pſal. <pb n="43" facs="tcp:63794:30"/> 27.13. &amp; 106.5. and in many other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to ſee is to feel, and not to ſee is not to feel or experience. And thus this Phraſe may be taken here; and ſo in this Senſe, theſe things are unſeen things to us; there's not a Man among us to day, that has once ſeen them, that has try'd and had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of them in himſelf, that can come out and ſay, I have gone through Death, I have been in Heaven, or I have been in Hell, and tried Things of another World. O Sirs, theſe things not ſeen are things we have not had an Experiment, a Proof, and Trial of; you have not had an Experiment of the things of Death, nor of the things of Judgment, nor of the things of Heaven, nor of the things of Hell. O think of it you that are drooping Saints, and Servants of God; you have not yet try'd, (1.) What it is to have God to wipe away all Tears from your Eyes. (2.) What it is to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Joy of your Lord. (3.) What it is to receive your Inheritance, to put on your Crown, and to poſſeſs your Kingdom. (4.) What it is to ſee God face to face, and to follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth. (5.) What it is to be with Chriſt your Lord and Love in Heaven. I ſay, all theſe, and all the unutterable things of Heaven, are things you have not tried: a Trial of them would make the whole World of ſeen things a Wilderneſs, a Wearineſs to you. And O think of it, you that are
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63794:31"/> daring Sinners, you that make nothing of Death, of Judgment, of Heaven, or Hell, I ſay again, think of it: you have not try'd the things you are making thus light of; you have not tried, I ſay, (1.) What it is to lie down in Sorrow. (2.) What it is to be driven away into outer and eternal Darkneſs. (3.) What it is to dwell with the devouring Fire, to dwell with everlaſting Burnings. (4.) What it is to be tormented with the Devil and his Angels. (5.) What it is to be puniſhed with everlaſting De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; had you ever tried theſe things, you would have other thoughts about them: they that are this Day trying them, and feeling what they are, are not making light of them; and O if you had been but a Year, a Week, a Day, or a Night, or an Hour in Hell, and ſeen what others are ſeeing, and felt what they are feeling, you would not think it a ſmall Matter to be damned. This is a Third; theſe things are unſeen, they are ſuch things that we have no preſent experimental Acquaintance with.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They are not preſent and entred on; they are not ſeen, that is, they are not yet in being as to us, we are not yet begun with them, and entred on them, we have them not preſent with us. This Phraſe of ſeeing, is uſed thus for enjoying, poſſeſſing, or having the Preſence of a Thing; John 3.3. <hi>Except a Man be born again, he can't
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63794:31"/> ſee the Kingdom of God.</hi> Videre regnum Dei idem eſt ac intrare in illud; therefore it's ſaid <hi>verſe</hi> the 5th,
<hi>Except a Man be born of Water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> Deut. 3.25. <hi>Moſes</hi> pray'd that he might ſee,
<hi>i. e.</hi> enter into and come to poſſeſs that good Land. So alſo, Pſal. 36.9. <hi>In thy Light we ſhall ſee Light,</hi> (i. e.) have or enjoy Light. So Luke 17.22. <hi>The Days will come when ye ſhall deſire to ſee one of the Days of the Son of Man, and ye ſhall not ſee it,</hi> that is, when you ſhall deſire to enjoy one of theſe Days, to have the preſence of one of theſe Days, and ye ſhall not ſee it, that is, ye ſhall not enjoy one of them, ye ſhall not have the Preſence of one of them with you. And ſo in many other Places, to ſee a Thing, is to have it preſent and in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion; and not to ſee a thing, is to have it abſent and unbegun with us. And in this reſpect alſo theſe things are unſeen things; that is, they are not begun with us, we are not entred on them, you and I are not yet entred on the things of Death, or the things of Judgment, on the things of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or on the things of Hell. O Sirs, the Saints Heaven, Harveſt and Happineſs is not yet begun, but to begin; the Saints Kingdom is not yet come, but to come. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Book
<hi>de Spectaculis,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading the Servants of God from them, hath this Motive, <hi>Noſtrae coenae, noſtrae nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae <pb n="46" facs="tcp:63794:32"/> nondum ſunt;</hi> So I ſay, the Saints Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs is not yet, it's yet out of ſight, and to come: And ſo, Sirs, the Sinners and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly's Hell, and Horror, and Torment, is not yet begun, but to begin. Do you ſee them Ranting and Revelling, Swaggering and Gallanting it out from Day to Day? O think it not ſtrange, for, I ſay, their Hell is not yet begun, they are yet in their Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and their Hell is to begin; their Time, nay, their Eternity of Darkneſs, and Chains, and Fire, and Weeping, and Gnaſhing, are yet to enter on. O conſider it you that live ungodly, I may ſay to you, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, James 5.5. <hi>Ye have lived in Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure on the Earth, and been wanton; and nouriſhed your Hearts as in a Day of Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Ay but where is it, Sirs, that you have lived? is it not on Earth, that you have lived thus in Pleaſure? is it not on Earth, that you are living? it's <hi>on Earth,</hi> it's on Earth only, and beyond Earth there's an unſeen Hell. How will you live there? will you live in Hell as you have lived on Earth, in Pleaſures, in Jollity, in Delicacy? will you take up a ſenſual Life, a delicate way of living, when you are in Chains, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Burnings, ſuffering the Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of an eternal Fire, and drinking whole Cups, nay Rivers of the Wine of the Wrath of God Almighty? O thoſe will be no Delicacies then, your Heaven will be paſt, as <hi>Luke</hi> 16.25. <hi>Thou in thy <pb n="47" facs="tcp:63794:32"/> Life-time receivedst thy good Things, and</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus <hi>evil Things: but now he is Comforted, and thou art Tormented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. I may add this: Unſeen things are things which are not conſidered, obſerved, or regarded; they are not ſeen, that is, they are not minded and regarded, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of by many. This Phraſe of ſeeing is uſed thus, for taking notice of, and care about a Matter; Pſal. 66.5.
<hi>Come and ſee the Works of God,</hi> obſerve and mark them. So
<hi>Mat.</hi> 22.11. <hi>And when the King came in to ſee the Gueſts, he ſaw there a Man which had not on a Wedding-Garment,</hi> when he came in to take notice of his Gueſts. Mat. 27.4. <hi>See thou to that,</hi> i. e. take thou care about that, look thou to that. So alſo <hi>verſe</hi> 24. <hi>See ye to it.</hi> And ſo here, we look (ſaith the Apoſtle) at things not ſeen, that is, we look at things that are little look'd at in the World, that are out of ſight, and out of mind with many; that many ne'r regard, or once trouble themſelves about. This is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in this reſpect alſo, theſe things of Death, Judgment, Heaven, and Hell, are as to many unſeen things; they mind them not, they take no more notice of them than if they were not: among the multitude of Thoughts that are within them and paſs through them every Day, there are none of this ſort, no ſerious pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Thoughts of the things of Death, <pb n="48" facs="tcp:63794:33"/> the things of Judgment, of Heaven, or Hell. O, Sirs, how many be there who have gone over twenty, thirty, forty Years, and yet, it may be feared, the Time is yet to come that ever they ſpent one ſingle Hour, Day or Night, Night or Day, one time or another, in ſerious Thoughts about unſeen things? pray look home, Sirs, to your own ſelves, and ſee what you have done in this Caſe. Theſe are, I ſay, with many unſeen things, things they are mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of, and careleſs about.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:63794:33"/>
            <head>SERMON III.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 4.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q> While we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen; for the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>FOurthly,</hi> We ſhall inquire, what Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at theſe unſeen things imports and implies.</p>
            <p>You ſee (1.) That there are unſeen things. (2.) What theſe unſeen things are. (3.) How they are unſeen. Now the next inquiry may be, what it is to look at unſeen things, or what this looking at unſeen things (which is the great Concern of Chriſtians) includes and implies. Now this Phraſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes and carries many things in it; I ſhall only at this Time point at theſe five that are bound up in it.</p>
            <p>To look at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs which are not ſeen, is a Phraſe that implies,</p>
            <p n="1">1. A real Valuation or Eſtimation of unſeen things, as things meet to be minded, and deſerving to be regarded by us. This
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:63794:34"/> Phraſe is thus uſed to denote that which deſerves to be regarded and valued; 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.14. <hi>And</hi> Eliſha
<hi>ſaid, As the Lord of Hoſts liveth, before whom I ſtand, ſurely were it not that I regard the Preſence of</hi> Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat <hi>the King of</hi> Judah, <hi>I would not look towards thee nor ſee thee;</hi> that is, I would not have matter'd, nor ſet by thee, it's <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> that I look at, and regard in the Matter. So here to look at unſeen things, is to reckon of them as valuable things, as things to be mattered and made account of by us. And this now, Sirs, is our Concern and Duty; it concerns thee and me, and lies on us, not to ſlight theſe unſeen things, as many do, as if they were poor, worthleſs, inconſiderable Matters, not worthy to be taken notice of or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded; take heed of this, reckon not of Death, of Judgment, of Heaven, of Hell, as ſorry, as inconſiderable things, as things too little and mean to be minded; but look at them, that is, make them Matters of Moment, Matters of Concernment, of greateſt Moment and Concernment of any Matters in all the World; for ſo they are, and ſuch they will be found with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of us another Day. If there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Death, Judgment, Heaven, Hell, to be minded or matter'd by us, who are on the way towards Death, Judgment, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or Hell; then there's ſurely nothing, nothing in the World, nor any thing out
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:63794:34"/> of the World, to be made any Matter of. What is it that you make a Matter of, that you look on as valuable, if theſe be nothing with you? ſurely, Sirs, theſe are things to be look'd at. And this is one, we muſt look at unſeen things, that is, get, and keep a home, a lively and affecting Impreſſion upon our Hearts, of the Weight and Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of unſeen things.</p>
            <p>Art thou a gracious Perſon, look at, that is, get and keep a-foot an affecting, an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding Senſe of the Height of unſeen Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thou art going to, of the Depth of unſeen Wrath thou art delivered from, and it will teach thee (whatever comes) to reckon as the Apoſtle our <hi>light Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> &amp;c. If Shame, if Loſs, if Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, if Perſecution: O what a ſmall Pain is this to the Glory to come? Art thou an ungodly profane Creature, O look at unſeen things, <hi>i. e.</hi> get and keep a-foot an abiding affecting Senſe of that eternal Glory thou art loſing, of that everlaſting Puniſhment thou art in danger to drop in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every Day, and every Hour. Either this would ſtartle thee out of thy preſent Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, or I know not what will.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Serious Meditation on them. This Phraſe is thus uſed, not only to denote ſomething that deſerves to be minded and regarded, but alſo to denote the minding and regarding of it, the imploying of our Thoughts about it. Prov. 24.32. <hi>Then I <pb n="52" facs="tcp:63794:35"/> ſaw, and conſidered it well: I looked upon it, and received Inſtruction:</hi> I look'd with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, obſerving, conſidering Eye. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. <hi>Look not on his Countenance;</hi> conſider it not, conclude not by that.
<hi>James</hi> 1.25. <hi>But whoſo looketh into the perfect Law of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> i. e. bendeth his Mind to meditate on it, and conſider it. So
<hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.1, 2. So here to look at things not ſeen, is to admit them into our ſerious Thoughts, to take them into our ſolemn Conſideration, and to ſet our muſing Minds at work about them. And this is our Concern and Duty, it concerns me, and it concerns thee, and every one that's here to day, to reckon of theſe things as M tters to be minded, and to mind them; to mind them, I ſay, and to transfer our moſt ſerious Thoughts to them. It's not enough to confeſs that they are Matters of Moment, a Thing that I think few will deny, but we muſt alſo mind them, and have our Thoughts exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed about them as Matters of ſuch Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a thing I fear that few practiſe. This is another thing that is implied in this looking, <hi>viz.</hi> ſerious thinking at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things: pray think of it, Haſt thou never thought of Death, Judgment, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or Hell, or at moſt only glanc'd at them, and caſt an Eye on them by the by, while thou haſt been minding other things? why know this Day, that it is thy Duty to look at them, to look, to fix the Eye of <pb n="53" facs="tcp:63794:35"/> thy Mind and Meditation on them, as thou doſt the Eye of thy Body on the Object thou wouldſt look narrowly upon, or accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately at. O they are things to be looked at, and not to be glanced at, things to be eyed with all Diligence, and not only on the by. Our Morning Thoughts, and our Evening Thoughts, our Day Thoughts, and our Night Thoughts, our Company Thoughts, and our ſolitary Thoughts, ſhould be meeting at theſe unſeen things, and ſpending themſelves on them, in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what a glorious bleſſed thing it will be to ſee the unſeen things of Heaven, and Glory we have hinted at, to ſee God, to ſee him as he is; and what a ſad and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing it will be, to ſee the unſeen things of Hell and Damnation, to ſee the Worm that never dieth, the unquenchable Fire, the Wrath to come. Theſe, Sirs, are Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that we ſhould look at, that is, our Thoughts ſhould fix, ſettle, and dwell much on them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Fixed Intention or Propoſal of them to our ſelves, as our great End or Aim: the original word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here uſed, ſignifies ſuch a looking as a Watchman uſeth that ſtands on a Tower to deſcry Enemies and Dangers and marks every Corner diligently; or ſuch a looking as an Archer when he is ſhooting, tho he have many Objects about him on this ſide, and on that ſide, yet he looks neither on this ſide, nor on the other ſide, <pb n="54" facs="tcp:63794:36"/> but ſtreight before him at the Scope or Mark he aims at. This, I ſay, is the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Word; and ſo to look at things not ſeen, is to make them our Scope and End, our great Mark and Aim in the World: and this now, Sirs, is our Concern and Duty alſo, it concerns me, and it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns thee, and it concerns every one, not only to value unſeen things, and to think on unſeen things, but alſo to aim at unſeen things; to make unſeen things our Mark, to eye unſeen things as the great Mark we ſhoot at. This is another thing, I ſay, that is implied in this looking, to wit, a ſteady aiming at unſeen things; we ſhould look on all other things, <hi>viz.</hi> ſeen things, as if we looked not, as By-buſineſſes; but we ſhould look at theſe unſeen things as our main Buſineſs, and End that we propound to our ſelves. Pray remember this, have you been making ſeen things, the ſeen Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, or ſeen Pleaſures, or ſeen Honours of the World, your great Matters, your great Marks that you have mainly deſigned and aimed at? why, alas, you have been looking the wrong Way; and all the while that you have been making this your Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, how to get Eſtates and Wealth, or how to raiſe your Names and Families, or how to take your fill of ſenſual Pleaſures; it has, I ſay, all the while concerned you, and lain on you as your Duty, to look at things not ſeen, to make unſeen things <pb n="55" facs="tcp:63794:36"/> your greateſt Matters. I ſay, it has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned you to make theſe your Buſineſs, theſe, theſe things ſhould have been your Matters, your Marks, your Aims, Sirs, <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) How you might get into a readineſs to ſee unſeen Death. (2.) How you might eſcape the things that are coming on this World, and ſtand before the Son of Man at his coming. (3.) How you might avoid the ſeeing of the unſeen things of Hell, the bottomleſs Pit, the Wine-preſs of the Wrath of God, the Darkneſs, Chains and Priſon of the Damned. And (4.) How you might be admitted to the ſeeing of the unſeen things of Heaven, in the Paradiſe, the City, the Temple of God; theſe are the things, the things you ſhould have been looking and aiming at all this while, and this is yet your great Concern and Duty in the World. Well, this is another; unſeen things are the things that we ſhould look at, that is, aim at.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It implies vigorous Proſecution or earneſt Endeavour, that we ſhould purſue them with all care and diligence. <hi>Iſa.</hi>
56.11. it's ſaid of the blind and greedy Watchmen, <hi>They all look to their own way, every one for his Gain from his Quarter,</hi> i. e. it's their great Matter they have in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, and are continually driving on. So here to look at things not ſeen, is to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue them as our great buſineſs in the World. As <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil. 3.14. <hi>I preſs toward the Mark,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63794:37"/> for the Prize of the High-calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Scopum verſus feror,</hi> that is, I have Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which is my Scope, or Mark, or End) in chaſe, I am making towards it up Hill and down, through thick and thin, as one reſolved never to reſt till I have attained unto it. This is to look at unſeen things, and this now Sirs, alſo is our Concern and Duty; it concerns me, and it concerns thee, not only to aim at, but alſo to lay out for unſeen things with all our Might: we muſt look at them as the Traveller that's on a Journey looks at the End of his Journey, or as a Runner that's in a Race, looks at the Scope or Mark he is to come to; the one runs with ſpeed, and the other rides with haſte, and both make towards the Mark. Thus I ſay, and on this faſhion we ſhould look at things not ſeen, as thoſe that are travelling or running towards them by earneſt Endeavour, in a diligent Uſe of all Means and Ways leading unto them. O, Sirs, we have many that are run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and riding, that are up early and late, that are toiling and moiling all the Day long, and of whoſe Labour there is no end. But what is all this about, what is it for? why alas, ſeen, ſeen things, theſe are the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters they are ſeeking; and as for unſeen things they either look not at them, or only ſo coldly and remi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, as if they cared not which end goes forward: but, Sirs, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns <pb n="57" facs="tcp:63794:37"/> you and me to be up and doing about unſeen things, to be looking, <hi>i. e.</hi> taking great Care, and ſeeking by all Means, early and late, to get a ſure-Title to, and to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our Intereſt in the unſeen things of Heaven and Glory. O theſe are the great Matters that Men and Women ſhould be, (1.) tirring about; (2.) Striving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; (3.) Labouring for; And (4.) preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing after in this World. This is another, unſeen things are the things we ſhould look at, that is, ſeek for, and purſue.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It implies earneſt Expectation, that we look at them as the great Object that we expect and deſire to obtain, and come to. Looking is thus put for Expecting; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.2. <hi>He looked that it ſhould bring forth Grapes.</hi> Verſe 7. <hi>He looked for Judgment, but behold Oppreſſion.</hi> Jer. 8.15. <hi>We looked for Peace, but no good came; and for a time of Health, and behold Trouble.</hi> 2 Pet. 3.13. <hi>We look for a new Heaven and a new Earth.</hi> In all which places Looking is put for Expecting. So here to look at unſeen things, is to look for unſeen things:
<hi>we look not at the things which are ſeen,</hi> that is, we expect not ſeen and Temporal things, as the things that our Portion and Happineſs lies in; but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen and Eternal things, are the things we are looking at, <hi>i. e.</hi> that we are waiting for, that we are in expectation of, that we are tarrying for; and this is alſo our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to look at, that is, make things not <pb n="58" facs="tcp:63794:38"/> ſeen our Expectations. Many look at ſeen things, and no further, having nothing either beſide them, or beyond them that they do indeed look for; ſeen things, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or other that's ſeen, is the utmoſt thing that they have in their Eye: but, Sirs, our looking ſhould be over, beyond, paſt all that is ſeen, to that that is not ſeen. 1 Cor.
1.7. <hi>Waiting for the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Phil. 3.20.
<hi>We look for the Saviour, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 2 Pet. 3.12.
<hi>Looking for the coming of the day of God.</hi> Why thus we ſhould look over, look paſt all that we are ſeeing, to that which is unſeen, as the great Matter we are in Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of. This now is the fifth thing; you ſee what looking at unſeen things imports, it carries theſe things in it. (1.) A valuing of. (2.) Thinking on. (3.) Aiming at. (4.) Seeking for. (5.) Expecting of things not ſeen. It's our Duty to look at things not ſeen; and to look at them, is to value them, to think on them, to aim at them, to ſeek after them, and to live in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them: then we look at theſe things when we make Account of them as Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the greateſt Moment, when we mind them as Matters of ſuch Moment, when we propoſe them to our ſelves as our great Buſineſs in the World, when we purſue them as our great Matter, and when we expect them as our Portion; all theſe are bound up in this looking, and meet in <pb n="59" facs="tcp:63794:38"/> this great Duty: from which we may ſee (by the way) that this Duty is a Duty that very few are living in at this Day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Why is it the Part and Duty of Chriſtians to look at unſeen things? You have ſeen, (1.) That there are unſeen things; (2.) What theſe are; (3.) How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen; (4.) What Looking imports. Our next Inquiry may be this, Why is it a Duty, and doth ſo much concern us to look at, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to eye, aim at, ſeek after, and to expect things which are not ſeen?</p>
            <p>Now this is our Duty, becauſe theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Certain and indubitable: they are not imaginary things, that conſiſt in No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Speculation only, but certain Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities; it's true, they are to us inviſible, but it's as true that they are as indubitable and unqueſtionable: we ſee them not now, but it is as ſure that they remain to be ſeen, as that there was a World to be ſeen, when we were lying in the Womb of our Mothers, and ſaw it not. Our Parents then ſaw a World that we were coming into, but we ſaw not a Heaven, an Earth, a Sun, theſe were out of our ſight; and many of them are now alſo ſeeing a World that we are going into, but ſee not. Sirs, there is a great certainty in theſe unſeen things, as in any thing that you ſee. (1.) Are you ſure there is a Sun in the Firmament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you ſee it with your Eyes? (2.) Are
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:63794:39"/> you ſure there is an Earth under your Feet, becauſe you ſee it and feel it? (3.) Are you ſure there are Men and Women be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides your ſelves on this Earth, becauſe you ſee them and converſe with them every Day? Why I tell you, it's not more ſure that there is a Sun an Earth, a Man or Woman beſides your ſelves, than this is, that there is an unſeen Death, Judgment, Heaven and Hell before you. I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hinted at many things of Heaven, and many things of Hell that are unſeen, that there is a Paradiſe, Houſe, City, Crown, Kingdom, reſerved for Saints in Heaven; and that there is a Darkneſs, Chains, Worm, Wrath, Fire, prepared for the wicked in Hell: and, Sirs, theſe are no Dreams or Fancies, but moſt certain things; it's not more ſure that I am ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, that you are hearing of them at this Time, than it is that there are ſuch things (tho we have never ſeen them) as we are now ſpeaking and hearing of. Therefore this may be one Reaſon why we ſhould look at them, they are certain, therefore certainly it concerns us to look at them. If it were a Matter only proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that there are unſeen things; if as much might be ſaid againſt them, as for them, then mindleſſneſs of them, and careleſſneſs about them, might be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what excuſable; tho in that caſe it would be a wiſe Man's part to take the ſureſt <pb n="61" facs="tcp:63794:39"/> ſide, and ſay, well I ſee it's a Queſtion, it's a Matter that is doubtful and dark, but I'll carry it ſo as I may not be at a loſs, and not know what to do if things prove ſo. I ſay, if theſe things were thus doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, yet it would be the part of a Wiſe Man to look at them: and then what ſhall we do when they are unqueſtionable, what ſhall we do, I ſay? doſt thou believe (Soul) that theſe unſeen things are certain, are unqueſtionable? and doſt thou not think it concerns thee to look at them? how can it be but thou muſt think ſo? Think on this, unſeen things are ſure things, all that I have been telling thee of is ſure, ſee thou to it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Unſeen things are very great, great in themſelves, of great Moment and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to us; yea the greateſt things and of greateſt Concernment to us: this may be another Reaſon. Sirs, unſeen things are not only ſure, but they are alſo very great things; they are no poor and trivial Matters, no light and inconſiderable things that are unworthy to be regarded, which are yet unſeen, yet inviſible, but (I ſay) great, greater than any thing that is ſeen, has been ſeen, or ſhall be ſeen before they come into ſight. This you may ſee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently from what is gone before. (1.) The Day of Judgment will be a great Day. Acts 2.20.
<hi>The Sun ſhall be turned into Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Moon into Blood, before that <pb n="62" facs="tcp:63794:40"/> great and notable Day of the Lord come.</hi> O it will be ſuch a Sight as this World never ſaw, to ſee Chriſt riding through the Clouds on his Chariot of Glory, to ſee the thouſands, ten thouſands of Angels, and all his Attendants. (2.) The things of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven are great things: to ſee God, and to ſee his Face, and to ſee him Face to Face, will be another manner of ſight than any of the things that are now ſeen. (3) The things of Hell are great things: the moſt tremendous things that have ever been ſeen in the World, are but very <hi>Nugae,</hi> to the Darkneſs, and Chains, Worm, and Fire of Hell. This, I ſay, may be another reaſon why you and I ſhould look at them, that is, mind them, they are very great things: if you be not looking at them, you are looking at ſomething elſe; and whatever it is that you have in your Eye, I tell you that it is very low, little, and inconſiderable; yea, nothing to thoſe things out of your ſight: go over all viſible things under Heaven, and the greateſt of them is leſs than the leaſt of thoſe inviſible things; the greateſt of the things called Good in this World, are nothing to the Good things of Heaven and Glory. <hi>Minima aeternae vitae Corona praeſtantior erit quam mille mundi, omnia ibi clara, omnia ibi chara, omnia ibi rara; ad illud coelum coeli etiam terrae noſtrae coelum terra eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:63794:40"/>The Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. having divided all things into viſible and inviſible, does again divide things inviſible, the things of Heaven, into Thrones, Dominions, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, Powers: mark here, he ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides the <hi>Inviſibilia, quae etiam exornat</hi> (as Beza <hi>in locum) iis nominibus quibus ſumma quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inter homines ſignificantur.</hi> And 1 Cor. 2.9. <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, neither have entred into the Heart of Man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> There is ſcarce any thing more vaſt and boundleſs than the Thoughts of Man, yet the things of Heaven are not only above what we ſee, but alſo above what we can think, and go beyond all our thoughts of them. And as to the greateſt of the things called
<hi>ill</hi> in this World, they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Ills of Hell and Damnation; this one word Hell or Damnation, Sirs, comprehendeth greater and more dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things in it, than all the amazing things that were e'r ſeen in this World. O, Sirs, we ſpeak much of unſeen things every Day; but the Truth is, we ſpeak little of them as they are; our Expreſſions, our Apprehenſions, our Thoughts of them are low, many of them unworthy, none of them reaching their Perfection. The Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> had heard much of
<hi>Solomon</hi>'s Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Magnificence, ſuch things had been reported to her, as were very wonderful, nay, incredible; ſhe could not believe them
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63794:41"/> till ſhe came and her Eyes had ſeen them; but then when ſhe ſaw, ſhe was forced to confeſs that the one half <hi>was not told her,</hi> 1 Kings 10.6, 7. Why thus the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of Chriſt tell us much of Death, and Judgment, and Heaven, and Hell, ſuch things as (I fear) many look on as incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, and not to be believed by them. But alas, when we come, and our Eyes have ſeen them, we ſhall cry out, O the one half, the thouſandth part was never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to us of that we now ſee; if thou go for Heaven, chuſe what thou haſt heard, or may hear e'r thou come thither, of the Glory of the Place, Company, Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Imployments, it's not the one half, nay, not the thouſandth part of what thou ſhalt ſee: if thou go for Hell, chuſe what thou haſt heard or may hear e'r thou come thither, of the Shame and Sufferings, there is not the one half, nay not the thouſandth part of what thou ſhalt ſee there. Thus theſe unſeen things are
<hi>Magna, maxima,</hi> Great, and greater than all other; therefore certainly it is our Duty and Concernment to look at them, that is, to mind them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Unſeen things are unavoidable: as they are certain in themſelves, and as they are very great, ſo they are alſo unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Unſeen things will come into ſight, are things that muſt be ſeen, you and I muſt ſee them: as it's unqueſtionable that <pb n="65" facs="tcp:63794:41"/> there are things lying out of our ſight, ſo it's as indubitable that they will all come into ſight, and you and I muſt ſee the unſeen things of Death, of Judgment, of Heaven, or of Hell.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Death is inevitable. Pſal. 89.48. <hi>What Man is he that liveth and ſhall not ſee Death? ſhall he deliver his Soul from the Hand of the Grave?</hi> What Man? no Man. Pſal. 49.6. <hi>They that truſt in their Wealth, and boaſt themſelves in the Multitude of their Riches:</hi> Ver. 7. <hi>None of them can by any means redeem his Brother, nor give to God a Ranſom for him:</hi> Ver. 8. <hi>(For the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Soul is precious, and it ceaſeth for ever)</hi> Ver. 9. <hi>That he ſhould ſtill live for ever, and not ſee Corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) <hi>As it is appointed for all Men once to die, ſo for them after Death to go to Judgment,</hi> Heb. 9.27. (1.) The particular Judgment of every Man immediately after Death. (2.) The general Judgment of all Men at the great Day; and as there is no way to avoid the ſeeing of Death, and Judgment after Death, no more (3) Is there any way to miſs ſeeing Heaven or Hell, after Death and Judgment. Of all that are gone before us, from the beginning of the World to this Day thorow ſo many Generations, there is not one that hath not ſeen what we ſee not, that is not ſeeing Salvation or Damnation this Day; and of all that are here to Day, there is not one Son or Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <pb n="66" facs="tcp:63794:42"/> not one Man or Woman that ſhall never ſee them; no, no, we muſt all ſee them: chuſe whether you will look at them or not now, you ſhall certainly look on them one Day. And therefore, Sirs, it doth ſurely concern us to take them into our Eye: if it were either a Queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any ſuch things, or a Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whether you or I ſhould ſee them, then to lay them out of our Eye might be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what excuſable. Ay, but Sirs, both theſe are out of all queſtion, and therefore queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſs it's a Matter that concerns us. This may be another reaſon why we ſhould look at them; unſeen things will come in ſight, other things are queſtionable: if thou be Sick, and would have Health, it's queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable whether thou muſt ever ſee it again; if thou be Poor, and would have Wealth; if thou be Perſecuted, and would have Peace, it's queſtionable whether thou ſhalt ever ſee theſe things: many in theſe and many other caſes, have never ſeen that which they have deſired to ſee, and many have eſcaped the ſeeing of that which they have been unwilling to ſee, and that would have been unwelcome to them, as in 2
<hi>Kings</hi> 22.20. Good <hi>Joſiah</hi> was taken away from ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Evil that God would bring upon <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> But here is, Sirs, no uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this Caſe; it admits of no Peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or may be. It is a Queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther e'r thou muſt have Health, or Peace, <pb n="67" facs="tcp:63794:42"/> but it's no queſtion whether thou muſt die and come to Judgment. It's a Queſtion whether thou muſt ever ſee the Good in the Land of the Living thou wouldſt ſee, or eſcape the Evil thou wouldſt not ſee: but it's no queſtion but if thou be a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſon thou ſhalt ſee the Goodneſs laid up in Heaven; and if thou be graceleſs, and die ſo, thou ſhalt without queſtion ſee the Fire, and Worm, and Wrath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Hell: theſe are ſure things. And now, Sirs, if unſeen things be thus cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, great, unavoidable, and things that muſt moſt ſurely be ſeen, then is there not a great deal of Reaſon that we ſhould look at them, and keep them ever in our Eye? And how ſadly do many miſcarry in this Matter, who only carry thoſe things in their Eye, that may and often do never come, and lay thoſe things out of their Eye that will moſt ſurely come?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Unſeen things are near: they are certain, they are great they are unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and they are alſo very near unto us, and therefore it doth certainly concern us to look at them. This may be another ground; ſuppoſe ſome great Matter i'th' World of much Concernment to you, tending to your making or undoing while you live, were now coming upon you, would you not look upon your ſelves as concerned to look at it? no queſtion but you would. Now this great ſeeing of <pb n="68" facs="tcp:63794:43"/> unſeen things is not a great way off, but at Hand, and hard by every one of you. As the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12. <hi>The Night is far ſpent, the Day is at Hand:</hi> So I may ſay to you, it's but as an Hour or two to Day-break, to Sun-riſe, that will inlighten things that are in Darkneſs. O, Sirs, you and I ſtand at the Door of theſe unſeen things; and if Death do but once open it by any one of its many thouſand Keys, we ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſee that which we have never ſee. Death (as I have told you) is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen thing, and it is <hi>Oſtium inviſibilium;</hi> here will be a beginning of them, and O how ſoon will this be here? Is there any more than a few Days, a Hand's breadth of Time, a Wind, a Breath, a Vapor, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween any of us and this? why verily there is no more. Job 14.1. <hi>Man that is born of a Woman is but of few Days.</hi> Pſal 39.5. <hi>Behold, thou haſt made my Days as a Hand's breadth, and mine Age is as nothing before thee; ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly every Man at his beſt State is Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> Job 7.7. <hi>O remember that my Life is Wind.</hi> Iſa. 2.22. <hi>Ceaſe from Man whoſe Breath is in his Noſtrils.</hi> James 4.14. <hi>For what is your Life? is it not a Vapour, that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peareth for a little Time, and then vaniſheth away?</hi> Do you not ſee many about you dropping away, one to day, and another to morrow, and a third the next Day? why all, all theſe go to ſee things not ſeen. Many, Sirs, are ſeeing theſe things to day, who ſaw them <pb n="69" facs="tcp:63794:43"/> not Yeſterday; and many ſhall ſee them to Morrow who are not yet ſeeing them to Day; and there are but yet a few, a very few Days, and there ſhall not be one of us who are here to Day, but we ſhall be landed on the Shore of unſeen things, to ſee them for ever, and never to ſee ſeen things more. Pray think of this, if unſeen things were a great way off, a long while too; if there were ſome Ages or Ce tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to go over us e re we ſhould ſee them, why it were ſomething b t alas, we know not, neither can we ſay, that there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Year, another Week, or another Day, between us and them; when we go out, we may ſee them e're we come in again; and when we come in, they may follow us at our back, and come in ſight as we are ſitting at our Boards, or lying on our Beds: ſhall we not then take them into our Eye, and mind them? O if we would but weigh the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, the Concernment and Propinquity of theſe things not ſeen, how could we ever lay them out of our Eye?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Unſeen things are eternal. (1.) They are
<hi>certain.</hi> (2.) They are <hi>momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous.</hi> (3.) They are
<hi>unavoidable.</hi> (4.) They are <hi>near,</hi> and they are alſo eternal and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable, therefore it doth unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly concern us to look at them; it will be but a while e're they come into ſight. Ay, but when once come into ſight, they'l tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eternally in ſight; this is the Reaſon
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:63794:44"/> the Apoſtle lays down here, why they looked not at ſeen but at unſeen things; <hi>For the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal.</hi> Here, my Beloved, we have the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſeen things of this World, and the unſeen things of the other World; the ſeen are temporal, the unſeen are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal: a Difference that puts an infinite Weight upon unſeen things, and makes them of infinitely more Concernment to us than any, than all things that are ſeen. I ſay, 1ſt. The things which are ſeen are but temporal; many have ſeen Health, and Peace, and Plenty, and Pleaſures, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, who are now gone from ſeeing them, and muſt never ſee them again: And many have ſeen Want, and Labours, and Travel, a Multiplicity and Variety of Troubles, who are alſo now gone from ſeeing them, and ſhall never ſee them more. And whatſoever we are now ſeeing in this World, whether of Comforts or Croſſes, of Peace or Trouble, we muſt ſee them but a while, and ſhall ſoon be ſailed out of their ſight for ever. All theſe ſeen things are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for a Seaſon, as the ſame word is rendred <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25. <hi>The Pleaſures of Sin for a Seaſon;</hi> for a time, as the ſame word, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.17. <hi>and have no Root in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo endure for a time;</hi> for a while, as
<hi>Mat.</hi> 13.21. Thus ſeen things, whatever they are, are but for a ſeaſon, for a time, <pb n="71" facs="tcp:63794:44"/> for a while; as <hi>Job</hi>
11.16. <hi>Becauſe thou ſhalt forget thy Miſery, and remember it as the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that paſs away, i. e.</hi> as that which is quickly gone, and ſhall never return again. When ſudden and great Showers of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fall, they make great Torrents and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undations in Brooks and Rivers; but theſe ſoon paſs away, and being once paſt they return no more. Why, on this faſhion the godly Man's Miſery is as Waters, and the ungodly Man's Proſperity is as Waters; and all theſe ſeen things are as Waters that paſs away. But now,
2dly. The things which are not ſeen are eternal and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, not for a ſeaſon, or a time, or a while, but for ever and ever, for Eternity. The things not ſeen in Heaven are Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is Life, and this Life is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; <hi>Mat.</hi>
25.46. <hi>But the Righteous into Life eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Salvation, and this Salvation is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; <hi>Heb.</hi>
5.9. <hi>And being made perfect, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Author of eternal Salvation unto all them that obey him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Inheritance, and this Inheritance is eternal; 1
<hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>An Inheritance incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, undefiled, and that fadeth not away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. A Crown, and this Crown is eternal; 1 Pet. 5.4. <hi>And when the chief Shepherd ſhall appear, ye ſhall receive a Crown of Glory that fadeth not away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:63794:45"/>5. A Kingdom, and this Kingdom is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal; 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. <hi>For an Entrance ſhall be adminiſtred to you abundantly, into the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Glory, and this Glory is eternal; 2 Cor. 4.17. <hi>For our light Affliction which is but for a Moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal Weight of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the things not ſeen in Hell are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, as there is,</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. A Pit, and this Pit is a bottomleſs Pit;
<hi>Rev.</hi> 9.1, 2. <hi>And the fifth Angel ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and I ſaw a Star falling from Heaven unto the Earth; and to him was given the Key of the bottomleſs Pit; and he opened the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit, and there aroſe a Smoke out of the Pit, as the Smoke of a great Furnace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly. Damnation, and this Damnation is eternal; <hi>Mark</hi>
3.29. <hi>But he that ſhall blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme againſt the Holy Ghoſt, hath never For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs, but is in danger of eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3dly. Deſtruction, and this Deſtruction is eternal; 2
<hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Who ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with everlaſting Deſtruction from the Preſence of the Lord, and from the Glory of his Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4thly. Darkneſs, and this Darkneſs is eternal;
<hi>Jude</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>To whom is reſerved the Blackneſs of Darkneſs for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5thly. A Worm, and this Worm is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; <hi>Mark</hi> 9.44.
<hi>Where the Worm dieth not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:63794:45"/>6thly. Fire, and this Fire is eternal; Mat. 25.41. <hi>Depart from me ye Curſed into everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> Well thus Sirs, you ſee the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between things ſeen and unſeen. (1.) Seen things are in continual Motion, unſeen things are immovable. (2.) Seen things paſs away as Waters ſwiftly, unſeen things ſtand ſtill as Weks through all Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations. (3.) The things we ſee here in this World, we ſee them but for Hours, Days, Weeks, or Years, and then they are no more. The things we muſt ſee hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the other World, we ſhall ſee for ever. Now Time determines and puts an end to our ſeeing of all that comes into ſight; then Eternity will never determine or put any Period to what ſhall be in ſight. And this Duration, this Eternity of unſeen things, puts (as I have ſaid) an infinite Weight upon them, and makes them of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely more Concernment to us than all ſeen things whatſoever. I ſay again, there are many things that call on us to keep an Eye on unſeen things, the Certainty of them calls us to take them into our Eye, and the Greatneſs of them, and the Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidableneſs of them, and the Nearneſs of them; but this their eternal Duration above all renders them to us as Objects that we are moſt concerned to eye. Here in this World we regard and matter things very much according to the Duration and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance <pb n="74" facs="tcp:63794:46"/> they are of. Things that are of ſhort Continuance and ſoon gone, we make no great reckoning of, whether great or ſmall, good or evil. A Flower, if never ſo ſweet and beautiful, if paſſing <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his Glory, is not much valued, becauſe we know it's fading, and will ſhortly loſe both its Sweetneſs and Beauty. An Ague, tho it make all the Body tremble, yet it's not much regarded, becauſe it will have but a few Paroxiſms or Fits, and then be gone; but things that are durable and of long Continuance, we uſe to account of: Whether good or evil, their Duration makes them conſiderable in our Eyes; and ſhall we not then make a Matter of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things in the other World, that will not only be of long and laſting, but of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and everlaſting Duration? O then what will we mind or matter? O Sirs, their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, their Eternity, Eternity makes them things to be look'd at before all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Matters: for
<hi>Aeternitas in bonis infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum bonum, in malis infinitum malum:</hi> This makes unſeen good things to be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely good and deſirable, and unſeen evil things to be infinitely evil and formidable. O think on this, if thou drop into Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there thou muſt ſee endleſs Woes and Wrath: If thou get to Heaven, there thou ſhalt ſee the Pleaſures that are for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Now doth it not concern thee to think how thou mayſt come to an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:63794:46"/> Happineſs, how thou mayſt ſcape an everlaſting Miſery? This may be another Ground of this Truth, the things not ſeen are interminable. And now I have done with the 5th Particular in this Point, and endeavour'd to ſhew you why it is that we muſt look at unſeen things; and you ſee that the unſeen things are, (1.) Certain. (2.) Great. (3.) Unavoidable. (4.) Near. (5.) Eternal. And therefore upon all theſe Accounts it cannot but appear to us as a Matter of very near and great Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to our ſelves, to look at unſeen things, if there be any thing either of Religion or Reaſon, Faith or Fear, Underſtanding or Senſe in us.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:63794:47"/>
            <head>SERMON IV.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 4.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q> While we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen; for the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE now come to improve the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. The firſt Uſe ſhall be an Uſe of Information. Is it the great Duty and Concernment of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to look at unſeen things? Then we may hence learn what things they are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That our great Concernments are lying in; a Matter that few underſtand or take notice of as they ſhould, and therefore let their Time, and Thoughts, and Cares, and Endeavours, run out on that that is not the Matter, the Buſineſs, that their great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern lies in, but on by-Buſineſſes and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable things, that are all nothing to the main. Pray Sirs, let us think of it, we are all buſy every day; one is planting, another is building, another is purchaſing, another is trading, another is tilling; one <pb n="77" facs="tcp:63794:47"/> is doing this, another is doing that, and every Body upon the Matter is taken up with ſomething or other, of the things which are ſeen; yet, alas Sirs! our great Matters, our great Concerns, lie neither in one or another of theſe ſeen things that are temporal, but in unſeen things which are eternal. Think on it Soul, to day, I ſay to thee, that whatever it is which thou art about, and moſt taken up with, amongſt things which are ſeen, this is not thy Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, this is not thy Buſineſs, this is not thy Great Concern, thou haſt a greater Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a greater Concernment than this to mind and tend, <hi>viz.</hi> thy future unſeen eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Eſtate. I ſay, Soul, the thing is, what ſhall be thine eternal Condition, what thou ſhalt ſee in another World for ever. Thy great Concernments lie in the things that are yet out of ſight. This is one thing we may learn hence; and O that you would take it into your Thoughts, and ſay to your ſelves, where are we, what are we doing? what is this we are buſying our ſelves about? are we not out, and off our great Concernment? O our Matter is not, 1. Where we dwell, what our Habitation is while among ſeen things, but where we ſhall take up our Lodging, and make our Abode when we are come to unſeen things. 2. Nor how we are accommodated with Lands, Meat, Drink, Clothes, Money and other Conveniencies now while ſeen things
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:63794:48"/> are preſent, but how we ſhall be accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated, what ſhall be our Portion, and where our Lines ſhall fall when we go to enter on and begin with things not ſeen, that we ſhall never end with. 3. Nor who are our Neighbours, our Friends and Relations, that we are now living and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journing among, converſing and company<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with, but who we muſt come to ſee, and be in Company of, and ſpend Eternity with, when we go to change ſeen Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, Friends and Relations, for others that are yet unſeen: They are thus our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things, and not our ſeen things, our eternal things, and not our temporal things, that are our great Concernments; our main Matters lie in Matters that are beyond all that our Eyes ſee under the Sun. Alas, Sirs, it's a common thing with many to ſay, upon meeting with ſome ſmarting Croſs, or ſad Loſs in their Eſtates, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, or Relations, O now I am undone, I am quite broken! and on the other ſide, if they meet with any ſpecial Succeſs in any of their Matters, or compaſs any of their Deſigns according to their Deſire, to ſay, O now I am made, now I ſhall be happy! But truly this is a great Miſtake, and you are much out when you ſay or think on this faſhion, for ſeen things can neither make you nor undo you, no body to this day was ever made or undone by them: they are unſeen things that will be a making or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing <pb n="79" facs="tcp:63794:48"/> to you; the unſeen things of Death and Judgment, of Heaven and Hell, are the making and the undoing things; and when theſe come in ſight, then you'l indeed be made, or undone, and that for ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may hence ſee that we have been and are a great way out of the way of our Duty many of us, it has been our Duty to be much in looking at unſeen things. O but, Sirs, have we not been little in our lookings this way, and to theſe things? Pray, Sirs, look a little back and take a ſerious review of what is paſt, and what you have been eying and minding all along, and then tell me if among the many things that you have look'd at, theſe unſeen things have not had the leaſt room in your Eye; and then I fear there will be but few, very few, exceeding few (if they'l deal truly) who muſt not confeſs that they have been very guilty in this particular.</p>
            <p>Alas, Sirs, not only our Rabble of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and diſſolute Perſons, or our Crouds and Companies of mere Worldlings have been Strangers to the Practice of this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but many that have looked towards Religion, have yet looked little towards this Duty: the Truth is, Sirs, there is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle looking at unſeen things. O who almoſt, (1.) Puts a Price on theſe? (2.) Who carries them in his Thoughts? (3.) Who ſet them before them as their Mark and Aim? (4.) Who goes after them? Or <pb n="80" facs="tcp:63794:49"/> (5.) Who is waiting with an earneſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation for them? Alas, ſeen things ſtand between us and unſeen things; and as they ſtand between us and unſeen things, ſo they come between us and looking at them; we look but little over them, or behind them. This is another thing; this Truth may convince a great many of us, that we are not looking the right Way, we are not looking at the right Object, or that which is our grand Concernment. Alas, Sirs, do we not Dine and Sup at our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed Times, go to Bed and riſe at our Hours, Converſe and Commune one with another as we were wont, Trade, and Till, and tend our Occaſions and Matters in the World Day after Day; but among all ſuffer Death to creep on us, Judgment to come towards us, and another World ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and haſten every Day, without taking them at all into our Eye, or looking at them on that manner that Matters of that Moment deſerve to be looked at? Truly, Sirs, this Text and Truth ſpeaks enough to ſhame us all: for where are the Men, the Women, the Chriſtians, the Profeſſors Young or Old, in one Condition or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that can ſay, we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen?</p>
            <p n="3">3. We may hence learn, that there are other things to be ſeen than thoſe that we have yet ſeen, or are ſeeing; we have
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:63794:49"/> not ſeen all that we muſt ſee: it was
<hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s Obſervation in his Time, that there was no new Thing under the Sun; Eccleſ. 1.9. <hi>The Thing which hath been, is that which ſhall be; and that which is done, is that which ſhall be done, and there is no new thing under the Sun: q. d.</hi> All things in this World have in all Ages been the ſame for Nature and Subſtance; there has been no Diverſity, Variety, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty, ſave in outward Circumſtances and Appearances of things; that that is now, is but the ſame o're again (in another dreſs) which has been afore, and that which ſhall be, will be no more but the ſame o're a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain which now is; and there is nothing new under the Sun. This he puts to Men that may ſeem otherwiſe minded, <hi>viz.</hi> to name the thing that may ſeem to be new; Ver. 10. <hi>Is there any thing whereof it may be ſaid, ſee, this is new?</hi> and then conſtantly affirms that it hath been in former time, <hi>it hath been already of old Time, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us,</hi> and only ſeems new to us becauſe length of Time, and ſhortneſs of Life have put it out of our remembrance, as they will alſo do things that now are out of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thoſe that are to come after: Ver. 11. <hi>There is no remembrance of former things; neither ſhall there be any remembrance of things that are to come, with thoſe that ſhall come after.</hi> Thus there is no new thing, but a circular Revolution and return of the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:63794:50"/> ſame things in ſeveral Ages, ſomething diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſify'd in their Circumſtances. Ay but there are new things above the Sun in the other World, things that have never been ſeen, nor ever ſhall be ſeen under the Sun; you and I have things to ſee that have not yet been ſeen by us at any time. This is another thing we may learn hence; and O take notice of it every one of you that are hearing it, both Saints, and Sinners; remember it you that fear God, and let it encourage you, you ſhall ſee other things than you are ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now from Day to Day in this Life. (1.) Are you ſeeing Creatures below your ſelves? you ſhall ſee your and their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in his Glory and Majeſty. (2.) Are you ſeeing Men made in your own Form and Likeneſs, compaſſed about with Infirmities, Corruptions, Temptations? you ſhall ſee the Holy Angels, and come to an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Company of them. (3.) Are you ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sinners running to exceſſes of Riot, and living without God in the World? you ſhall ſee Glorious Saints ſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne, and ſerving God Day and Night in his Temple. (4.) Are you ſeeing Shame, and Reproach, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt? you ſhall ſee Glory, and Honour, and receive a Crown of Glory that fadeth not away. (5.) Are you ſeeing Want, meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Poverty, Neceſſities, and Straits? you ſhall ſee endleſs Fulneſs, a bleſſed Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, where you ſhall never ſee Want of <pb n="83" facs="tcp:63794:50"/> any thing again for ever. (6.) Are you ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Labours and Travel? you ſhall ſee ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Reſt. O, Sirs, you that are going for Heaven, have that to ſee that will make amends for all the Evil and Trouble you are now ſeeing: Heaven, Heaven compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends all that Good that can poſſibly fall within the Compaſs of your Thoughts or Apprehenſions. And O remember this, you that forget God, you have a fine time of it (as you think) now, while you walk in the ways of your Heart, and in the ſight of your Eyes; and it were ſomething if you were never to ſee any thing but what you are now ſeeing. O but there are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things, and you muſt ſee other things than thoſe you are now ſeeing from day to day: You are now ſeeing Peace, and Plenty, Pleaſure and Proſperity: Ay, but you have Trouble and Want, Pain and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſee. I pray think of it, you know the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> when he was ſeeing the Pomp and Glory of his Royal Feaſt, had ſomething that he never thought of coming into his ſight, which put him under a great Conſternation; Dan. 5.5, 6. <hi>In the ſame Hour came forth Fingers of a Man's Hand, and wrote over againſt the Candleſtick, upon the Plaiſter of the Wall of the King's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; and the King ſaw the part of the Hand that wrote. Then the King's Countenance was changed, and his Thoughts troubled him, ſo that the joints of his Loins were looſed, and his <pb n="84" facs="tcp:63794:51"/> Knees ſmote one againſt another.</hi> And now this ſtrange, this ſudden Sight, marred all his Mirth and Muſick: Lords and Ladies, Crowns and Kingdoms could not relieve him; but his Countenance changed, his Joints looſened, and his Knees ſmote one againſt another. Why, Sirs, this is your Caſe, your very Caſe this day; you are ſeeing your Comforts and Pleaſures, but have that to ſee that will marr all your Mirth for ever. O that you would conſider it this Day, if his Countenance was thus changed only upon ſeeing the Fingers of a Man's Hand writing over againſt him; O then how will it be with you, when you have the bottomleſs Pit, and all the tremendous things therein coming into your ſight? Well, Sirs, this is another thing you may learn hence; there are other things to ſee than are now ſeen.</p>
            <p>Second Uſe, of Reproof. Is it the great Duty and Concernment of all to look at unſeen things? then this may reprove thoſe,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Who look only at ſeen things, things which are in ſight, as the Gain, and Glory, and Pleaſures of this preſent World, but never look ſo far as another World, as unſeen things. And this is a very common thing many do on this manner: A great many muſt ſay, (if they'll ſay the Truth, and their Practices ſay it for them every
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:63794:51"/> Day) we look not at the things which are not ſeen, but at the things which are ſeen. Theſe are the things which we eye, and mind, and purſue, and are in travel after, early and late, how we may compaſs them, and come by them; I ſay, this is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Caſe of a great many: I fear there is no want of thoſe here to day, who do on this faſhion, that have ſomething or other in their eye of the things that are ſeen. Now if thou be one of them, I would tell thee, and pray thee conſider it, that this Courſe is a
<list>
                  <item>1. Brutiſh,</item>
                  <item>2. Paganiſh,</item>
                  <item>3. Faithleſs,</item>
                  <item>4. Fooliſh,</item>
                  <item>5. Ruining,</item>
               </list> Courſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This Courſe is a brutiſh Courſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for Beaſts, who have only Senſe to lead them, but no Reaſon to guide them; not at all becoming Men who are reaſonable Creatures. I ſay, it's the part of Brutes, who have no higher part than Senſe, only to look at ſeen and preſent things: thou degradeſt thy ſelf from the Degree and Excellency of a Chriſtian; nay, thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradeſt thy ſelf from the Degree of a Man, and putſt thy ſelf into the Form of a Beaſt, while thou lookſt only at ſeen things; nay, thou throwſt thy ſelf below ſome Brutes in this, that being void of Reaſon, yet look further than only to what is juſt ſeen, and preſent. The ſilly Ant in Summer looks as <pb n="86" facs="tcp:63794:52"/> far as Winter, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.6, 7, 8. and the Stork, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.7. knows its ſeaſon. And wilt thou be like the Beaſts? nay, worſe than the Beaſts that periſh? Shall the weak Ant, the poor Stork, the ſmall Crane, and the Turtle, and the Swallow, ſilly and contemptible Creatures, condemn thee? What an Abſurdity, what a Shame is this? What haſt thou Reaſon for, if thou wilt make no uſe of it, nor diſtinguiſh thy ſelf by it in thy Practice from a Beaſt, when God hath by giving it to thee, diſtinguiſh'd thee from them in thy Being? Pſal. 8.6. <hi>Thou madeſt him have Dominion over the Works of thy Hands, thou haſt put all things under his Feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This Courſe is a Paganiſh Courſe: if thou wert a very Pagan, one of the worſt of the Heathens, and among a Nation of Barbarians, thou couldſt but do on this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. Mat. 6.32. <hi>For after all theſe things do the Gentiles ſeek:</hi> After theſe preſent things, and after theſe ſeen things, theſe poor Pagans who are either wholly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and know nothing of theſe unſeen things, or at beſt have but very dark and imperfect Apprehenſions of them, and do but give a faint and weak Aſſent to them, are taken up with, and acquieſce in ſeen things: and ſhall there be no Difference? Shall Chriſtians who differ ſo far from Pagans in Profeſſion, agree with them in Practice? Shall Chriſtians now juſtify Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, <pb n="87" facs="tcp:63794:52"/> and Heathens hereafter condemn Chriſtians? How great will that Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation be? O think of this you that never look further than you can ſee with Eyes of Fleſh; what a foul and groſs thing is it, that you who have the Goſpel, the lively Oracles of the living God, plain, open, Noon-day Diſcoveries of unſeen things, of unſeen things that are ſo great, ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable, ſo near and Eternal, ſhould as the
<hi>Gentiles</hi> only look at ſeen things?</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Courſe is a faithleſs Courſe. I know that you'l profeſs to have Faith, and ſay, that you are Believers: but pray, Sirs, what have you Faith for, or what uſe make you of it? Is not Faith the Evidence of things not ſeen? Doth it not lead to look at things not ſeen? Why, verily this is the Work of Faith, the Office of Faith: and therefore while you only look thus at things ſeen, and make them your Matters and Marks, you do proclaim your ſelves to be Men and Women void of Faith. O there's hardly a greater Argument of Infidelity than this; any thing that doth more ſpeak Perſons to be very Infidels than this; I would you would think of it. If you had but Faith as a Grain of Muſtard-ſeed, there would be ſome looking beyond things that are in ſight. And ſurely Sirs, if you be a faithleſs Generation now, you ſhall be a Chriſtleſs and Heavenleſs Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to Eternity.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:63794:53"/>4. This Courſe is a fooliſh, a very fooliſh Courſe; this is another, it's brutiſh, and it's alſo fooliſh: for pray what are theſe ſeen things that you are ſetting in your Eye? they are but,</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. The Footſtool of God; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.1. <hi>The Earth is my Footſtool.</hi> Sirs, all the Crowns, Thrones, Scepters, Robes, and other great things of the World, are but the Footſtool of the God of Heaven. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou lookſt on, and art ſet on here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun, why it's but a piece of God's Footſtool; it's but what he puts and keeps under his Feet; and wilt thou ſet thine Heart on that he ſets his Feet on? What is Folly if this be not, to neglect looking after a Place before the Throne of God, only to gather up and fill thy Boſom with ſome Chips of his Footſtool, when and while thou haſt as fair an Opportunity for that as for this? None but Children and Fools would take up with painted Pebbles when they have pure Gold before them. What are they that chuſe to lie at the Footſtool, when there is open way of aſcending before the Throne?</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. This World is the Walk of the Devils, where God permits the Devil to have his Rounds from one Generation to another; <hi>Job</hi> 1.7.
<hi>And the Lord ſaid unto Satan, From whence comeſt thou? and Satan anſwered the Lord, and ſaid, From going to and fro in the Earth, and from walking up and <pb n="89" facs="tcp:63794:53"/> down in it.</hi> This is Satan's Walk, and here he walks not as an idle Spectator, but as a buſy Tempter and Deſtroyer, making it his continual Buſineſs to ſeduce, blind, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, enſnare Men, and make them both as bad and as miſerable as himſelf. I ſay, the Earth is his Walk, and ſeen things in it are his Baits, his Snares, his Tools, whereby he deſtroys hundred thouſands of Souls: yea, while we look at ſeen things, reſt in ſeen things, content our ſelves with our ſeen things, he walks among them, and can in a Moment (if God but looſe his Chain) turn us out of all our ſeen things, as we may ſee in
<hi>Job</hi>'s Caſe; <hi>Job</hi> 1. 6, 7. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto Satan, Behold, he is in thine Hand, but ſave his Life. So went Satan forth from the Preſence of the Lord, and ſmote</hi> Job <hi>with ſore Boils, from the ſole of his Foot unto his Crown,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. Seen things are the World's Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Cruſt that God caſts out to Dogs, as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid of the Turkiſh Empire. Job
9.24. <hi>The Earth is given into the Hand of the Wicked:</hi> he ſuffers them to have a poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and uſe of the things thereof, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves nothing of the things of the Earth from them, as things they may not ſhare in; what canſt thou name of the things here, that Wicked Men of the World have not had? The Apoſtle reduceth the things that are in the World, that are ſeen, to three Heads, 1 John 2.16. <hi>The Luſt of the Fleſh, <pb n="90" facs="tcp:63794:54"/> the Luſt of the Eyes, and the Pride of Life;</hi> i. e. Pleaſures, Poſſeſſions, Honours: Now all theſe are the World's Portion, and Wicked Men have had a Fulneſs of them. (1.) Pleaſures; James 5.5. <hi>Ye have lived in Pleaſure on the Earth,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, ſpeaking to wicked Men. (2.) Poſſeſſions; Job
21.13. <hi>They ſpend their Days in Wealth.</hi> Pſal. 73.7. <hi>Their Eyes ſtand out with Fatneſs, they have more than Heart could wiſh.</hi> (3.) Preferments; Dan. 4.17. <hi>The Moſt High ruleth in the Kingdom of Men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will, and ſetteth up over it the baſeſt of Men.</hi> Wicked Men have all along had, and have all theſe, O Soul, the things thou now ſeeſt, even the ſineſt, and faireſt, and fulleſt of them, are but things that many a Man has had, who is now in Hell, and things that many have who muſt never come to Heaven. (1.) Is it a fine Houſe that thy Eye is on? many a one has dwelt in a fine Houſe, who is now dwelling in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. (2.) Is it fine Clothes thou lookſt at, how thou mayſt go Gallant, and be all in the Mode? Why, alas, many that have been clothed in Purple and fine Linen, and decked with all manner of Ornaments, are now ſwimming naked in Rivers or Fire and Brimſtone. (3.) Is it great Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions thou art looking at, Houſes, Lands, Treaſures? why many a one hath laid Houſe to Houſe, and Field to Field, and Heap to Heap, that now lack a drop of <pb n="91" facs="tcp:63794:54"/> Water. Now is it not a fooliſh Courſe to look only at, and keep an Eye on that which is no better than the Portion of the World, of the Men that muſt never come to Heaven? What thinkſt thou of it? art thou doing wiſely, while thou art go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after nothing but what's ſeen, when there's nothing of that that's ſeen, but God allows it to thoſe that are going for, and muſt to Hell?</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. Seen things are the Subject of God's Curſe; this was laid upon theſe ſeen things as ſoon as Man was fallen. Gen. 3.17.
<hi>Curſed is the Ground for thy ſake;</hi> the Ground, that is, all this viſible World, <hi>for thy ſake, propter te,</hi> i. e. <hi>propter pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum tuum, vel quod attinet ad te</hi> (Piſcator.) Under this Curſe it lies to this Day, to the Men of the Earth, and with this it comes accompanied to their Door. (1.) Their Treaſures carry a ſecret Curſe in them. (2.) Their Poſſeſſions have a Curſe reſting on them. Prov. 3.33. <hi>The Curſe of the Lord is in the Houſe of the Wicked.</hi> Theſe ſeen things are left to be as Fuel to their Luſts, as Food to their Pride, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, and Luxury, as Snares to their Souls. Now, Sirs, is it not a fooliſh thing for Men to ſet their Eye on nothing but a
<hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Garment, an <hi>Achan</hi>'s Golden Wedg, an accurſed thing?</p>
            <p n="5">5thly. Seen things are Fuel prepared for Burning, combuſtible Stuff that Doomſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day <pb n="92" facs="tcp:63794:55"/> will make an end of; all theſe things that are now ſeen, are things that muſt all be burnt up before our Eyes. 2 Pet. 3.7. <hi>The Heavens and the Earth which are now, are reſerved unto Fire againſt the Day of Judgment.</hi> Ver. 10. <hi>The Earth alſo, and the Works that are therein ſhall be burnt up.</hi> Thus all theſe ſeen things are kept for Fire, a Fire is kindling in their Bowels that will turn them into cold Aſhes; think on this pray, a Fire is coming, a Fire is coming upon all the Gain of the World; a Fire is coming upon all the Glory of the World; a Fire is coming upon all the Poſſeſſions of the World; a Fire is coming upon all the Habitations of the World, nothing ſhall be left, nothing ſaved, not a penny of thy Money, not a Stick or Stone of thy Houſe, not a Foot of thy Land.</p>
            <p>Well, this is a fourth thing; this Courſe is a fooliſh Courſe, for all theſe ſeen things are but the Footſtool of God, the Devils Walk, the World's Portion, the Subject of God's Curſe, Fuel for the Fire at Doomſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day; and is it not a very poor ſorry Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, for Men and Women then to look no further than theſe, no further than the Footſtool? O that Men ſhould ſo far loſe themſelves, is both ſad and ſtrange!</p>
            <p n="5">5. This is a ruining and an undoing Courſe, many have been undone by it; and it's marked out as a way to Perdition, Phil. 3.18, 19.
<hi>(For many walk, of whom I <pb n="93" facs="tcp:63794:55"/> have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are the Enemies of the Croſs of Chriſt; whoſe End is Deſtruction, whoſe God is their Belly, and whoſe Glory is in their Shame, who mind earthly things):</hi> Here the Apoſtle ſhews, that there were many who were walking towards Deſtruction, and whoſe Way would end therein. And he doth further particularly name ſeveral ſorts of them; and among the reſt you ſee this ſort of Perſons are one, <hi>who mind earthly things,</hi> who are wiſe about earthly things. Thus minders (I pray you take notice of it) of earthly things are marked for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; that is, ſuch as only look after, are buſy about, taken up with, and aim at theſe Preſents and Viſibles. O, Sirs, this looking at ſeen things, is the loſing of the Soul and unſeen things for ever. It was a Saying that Sir
<hi>Thomas Moore</hi> uſed, <hi>There is a Devil called</hi> Negotium,
<hi>Buſineſs, that carrieth more Souls to Hell, than all the Devils in Hell beſides.</hi> O this Buſineſs, this mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of earthly things, this looking at ſeen things, undoes thouſands. Sirs, if you could ſpeak with many now in Hell, and ask them what was their undoing? they would ſurely tell you it was this: O this, this was our ruin.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) We were thinking what we ſhould eat, and drink, and wherewithal we ſhould be clothed, when we ſhould have been making proviſion for our Souls.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:63794:56"/>(2.) We were plodding for Poſterity, when we ſhould have been preparing for Eternity.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) We were ſurveying our Eſtates, when we ſhould have been looking into our Hearts.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) We were caſting how to drive on our Bargains, to contrive our Buſineſs, and compaſs our Ends, when we ſhould have been working out our Salvation. And theſe, theſe things were our undoing; while we were thus buſy, early and late, about Earth, we loſt Heaven. When we were in the World, we minded ſeen things, we loved ſeen things, we were ſet on ſeen things; and when we came to leave the World, God told us we had that which we choſe: this would be the Language of many a Soul! And now, Sirs, will you take the way that many have met with ruin in, that is marked as a way to Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            <p>This is the firſt Word by way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, to thoſe who look only at ſeen things, at things which are in ſight. You ſee it is a Brutiſh, a Paganiſh, a Faithleſs, a Fooliſh, an Undoing Courſe: Will you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in ſuch a Courſe? will you follow Pagans and Brutes? will you live as Men without Faith and without Knowledg? O learn this Leſſon, this Duty, to look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:63794:56"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thoſe are to be reproved by this Doctrine, who live as if there were no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things, no Judgment to come, no Heaven, no Hell, nothing but what is ſeen, and what is preſent. My Beloved, there are multitudes of theſe in our Day: you ſhall not meet with many who will ſay, there are no unſeen things. But as one ſaith,
<hi>Impuriſſima &amp; profaniſſima illa vita quam maxima pars hominum ſectatur, perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuè indicat quod non ſentiant eſſe vitam poſt hanc.</hi> They live juſt as if they had no more to do, than to rant, and drink, and roar, and revel, and die, and ſo an End of all for ever; or as if they had nothing to do, but rake as much as they can of the World together, whether by Right or Wrong, and then die; behind which there is nothing. My Friends, are any of you of this Make of Perſons, ſuch as are lying in Wickedneſs, as giving your ſelves up to Profaneneſs? Pray tell me, what have you thought, what are you thinking of? Have you ever thought, or do you ever think in earneſt of unſeen things, or that there are any unſeen things; that there is any ſuch thing as a Judgment to come, or a Hell that the Wicked are to be turned into? I ſay, what do you think? Are there any unſeen things, or are there not? If you ſay that there are, and be perſwaded that there are things out of ſight, as you are told of, and as have been hinted to you from <pb n="96" facs="tcp:63794:57"/> this Subject, then how can you, dare you live on ſuch a faſhion? Do you believe <hi>that the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, with his mighty Angels, in flaming Fire, taking Vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting Deſtruction from the Preſence of the Lord, and from the Glory of his Power?</hi> as you have it 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9. Do you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that <hi>the Kings of the Earth, and the great Men, and the rich Men, and the chief Captains, and the mighty Men, and every Bond-man, and every Free-man, ſhall hide themſelves in the Dens, and in the Rocks of the Mountains; and ſay to the Mountains and Rocks, Fall on us, and hide us from the Face of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the Wrath of the Lamb: For the great Day of his Wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand?</hi> Rev. 6.15, 16, 17. Do you believe <hi>that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God? nor Fornicators, nor Idolaters, nor Adulterers, nor Effeminate, nor Abuſers of themſelves with Mankind, nor Thieves, nor Covetous, nor Drunkards, nor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilers, nor Extortioners, ſhall inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God?</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9, 10. Do you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that <hi>the Fearful, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelieving and Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, and Murderers, and Whoremongers, and Sorcerers, and Idolaters, and all Liars, ſhall have their part in the Lake which burneth with Fire and Brimſtone?</hi> Rev. 21.8. Why
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:63794:57"/> then you muſt believe alſo, Sirs, that you are by theſe your doings, undoing your ſelves, damning your ſelves, ſinking your ſelves to Hell for ever. You muſt believe there is a time a coming on you, when you'l be put to cry to the Mountains and Rocks to fall on you, when you muſt be excluded from an eternal weight of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and lie down in everlaſting Flames.</p>
            <p>And if you ſay, or think there are no unſeen things, you'l be ſadly diſappointed and deceived, for (as you have here ſeen) they are both ſure and unavoidable, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo near unto you; and it's but a while and you will all be convinced, (and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond any poſſibility of ever making a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of it again to Eternity) that Death is not the End of all things with you, that all's not done when the Body falls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Duſt, but that there's then a Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, a beginning that ſhall never have ending, of things that now are out of ſight: pray think of it; and as you would not ſee everlaſting Sorrows, everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Weepings, everlaſting Damnation, break with your preſent Courſes, and live as thoſe that look for the coming of things unſeen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:63794:58"/>
            <head>SERMON V.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 4.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q> While we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen; for the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> IT may reprove Chriſtians, thoſe that have made Religion their Buſineſs more than others, that they have not made this their Buſineſs more, been no more careful,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) In looking at unſeen things; (2.) In aiming at; (3.) In ſeeking of; (4.) In following after; (5.) In clearing their Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the unſeen things of Heaven and Glory.</p>
            <p>Alas, Sirs, this is verily a Fault among Chriſtians, we are much in looking at ſeen, but we are little in looking at unſeen things. That you may not live in this Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect, but be more in looking this way, pray conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That you are not much concerned to look after ſeen things, for they are but <pb n="99" facs="tcp:63794:58"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they'l not laſt as long as Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity laſts; nay, they'l not reach another World, not go one ſtep with you in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World: As ſoon as ever you are paſſed into another World, <hi>The former things are paſſed away,</hi> Rev. 21.4.
<hi>i. e.</hi> all the things that are preſent, both good and bad: none of the ill things of the preſent World will follow the Saints into another World; nor will any of the good things of the preſent World, follow Sinners into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World: Seen things laſt but a while, reach but a little way.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Unſeen things are the beſt things, better than any thing that is ſeen; weigh what you will againſt them, and you'l find they can bear no weight with the things of Heaven. As,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) If you weigh againſt them Riches, Gold, Silver, all the Treaſures of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and hidden Store of ſecret Places, yet they'l all be inconſiderable, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to nothing, leſs than a Drop of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Ocean, than a lump of Lead to a Mountain of Pearl; they are things of no worth in Heaven, things that have no place in Heaven: It's a Country (as the Martyr ſaid) where Money bears no maſtery, where that that goes here for Hundreds and Thouſands, will not go for Pence and Farthings.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) And if you weigh againſt them Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Powers, and Greatneſs, why <pb n="100" facs="tcp:63794:59"/> as little is there in them to bear any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with the things of Heaven; add theſe to the former, and put both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (<hi>viz.</hi> all the Treaſures, and all the Crowns and Kingdoms under Heaven) in the Ballance with the Crown and Kingdom of Heaven, and they'l be leſs than little to them.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) If you weigh Pleaſures againſt them, you ſhall ſtill find they weigh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; add theſe to the two former, even all the Delights of the Sons of Men, and put all three together in the Ballance with the unſeen things of Heaven, and they will be of no weight; unſeen things are the beſt things, there is no worth in Riches to the Riches of Glory, there is no weight in Crowns to the Crown of Glory, there is no ſweetneſs in Pleaſures to the Pleaſures, the Rivers of Pleaſures at God's right Hand.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Nothing ſhort of unſeen things is of any moment, or worth looking at; unſeen things are not only the beſt things that you or I can look at, but there is nothing elſe we can look at that is of any moment. The Holy Ghoſt ſpeaking of ſeen things, uſeth moſt diminiſhing Terms, he calls Wealth <hi>thick Clay,</hi> Hab. 2.6. <hi>Wo to him that ladeth himſelf with thick Clay.</hi> The Duſt of the Earth, <hi>Amos</hi> 2.7. They <hi>pant after the Duſt of the Earth.</hi> Wind, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi>
5.16. <hi>What Profit hath he that hath laboured <pb n="101" facs="tcp:63794:59"/> for the Wind?</hi> Graſs, and the Flower of the Graſs, <hi>James</hi> 1.11. <hi>The Sun is no ſooner riſen with a burning Heat, but it withereth the Graſs, and the Flower thereof falleth, and the grace of the faſhion of it periſheth: ſo alſo ſhall the rich Man fade away in his Ways.</hi> He ſtiles Power, and Pomp, and Glory, Fancy, <hi>Acts</hi> 25.23. The whole World a Surface, an Out-ſide, an empty Shadow, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31. <hi>For the Faſhion of this World paſſeth away.</hi> A vain ſhew,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.6. <hi>Surely every Man walketh in a vain ſhew.</hi> On this faſhion the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaks of theſe ſeen things; and ſurely on this faſhion, they who are ſeeing unſeen things, are thinking of ſeen things to day; the beſt, the greateſt, the choiceſt of them, are but Clay, and Duſt in their Eyes. Alas, look but on ſeen things in the Glaſs of Scripture, and you'l ſee there is nothing in ſight that deſerves to be look'd at; they are either unſeen things, or nothing that you muſt make your Object, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.2, 3.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All your Happineſs lies in things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen. Thoſe Grecians loſt the Comfort of their Lives, (ſaith the Hiſtorian) who ſaw not <hi>Alexander</hi> ſit in <hi>Darius</hi>'s Throne. I may ſay, thoſe loſe the Comfort of their Lives, that don't lift up their Minds to the high things belonging to the heavenly Throne. <hi>Niſi ad haec admitterer, non fuerat operae pretium naſci.</hi> Alas, there is no true and ſolid Happineſs to be had in ſeen <pb n="102" facs="tcp:63794:60"/> things; all the things that are under the great Vault of Heaven, and on this ſide the Sun and Moon, (how fair ſoever they look) are but the droſſy part (as we ſay) of God's Creation: Like the Goats-hair and Badgers-skins on the Tabernacle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, that was overlaid with Gold within; Gold within, and Skins without; ſo, I ſay, theſe ſeen things are but very ſorry things, poor Shadows, empty Vanities, broken Ciſterns; nothing to unſeen things, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that can make us happy.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Your unalterable and unchangeable Happineſs lies in unſeen things, not in any thing that is in ſight. It's true, ſometimes ſeen things may have ſuch a kind and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Aſpect towards you, as may tempt you to ſay as <hi>David</hi> once, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.6, 7. That your Mountain is made to ſtand ſtrong, and you ſhall never be moved. But as he was preſently convinced of his Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, ſo will you find yours; for, alas, this World is the Stage of Changes and Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, wherein all things are on a Wheel and in motion. (1.) The Sun riſes and ſets; (2.) Seas ebb and flow; (3.) Winds riſe and fall; (4.) Rivers run Day and Night; (5.) Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Kingdoms are up and down; (6.) Perſons and Families are coming up and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down; (7.) Rich and Poor are meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. 1 Sam. 2.4, 5. <hi>The Bows of the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are broken, and they that ſtumbled are girt with ſtrength. They that were full, have hired out <pb n="103" facs="tcp:63794:60"/> themſelves for Bread; and they that were hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, ceaſed: ſo that the Barren hath born ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ſhe that hath many Children is waxed feeble.</hi> All things are (as we ſay) on their Feet, none can ſit or lie; ſome go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſome go forward: it were endleſs to enumerate the Changes that are acted every day upon the Stage of this World; here is no conſtancy, no ſtability in any thing, this is only to be found above in the unſeen World, and there all things are unchangeable and unalterable for ever. (1.) God the Portion and Happineſs of his Choſen, is unchangeable; (2.) Angels unchangeable; (3.) Saints unchangeable; (4.) The heavenly Manſions unchangeable; (5.) The Riches of Glory; (6.) The Joy in God's Preſence; (7.) The Pleaſures at his right Hand, are for evermore; here will be an unchangeable unalterable State of Reſt and Happineſs, without any Flux or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux, Change or Variation, for ever. O therefore Chriſtians, check your ſelves that you have not looked, that you are not look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more at unſeen things, and longing more to come unto the ſeeing of them. It's reported of great <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that he ſhould ſay when he was dying, <hi>I rejoice that I am now going out of a World of Contraries.</hi> How much more may the ſerious Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, to think of going out of a World of Contraries, and off a Stage of Changes, to unchangeable Bleſſedneſs?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:63794:61"/>The third Uſe, is a Uſe of Exhortation. Is it the great Part, Duty, and Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſtians to look at unſeen things? then it may be for Exhortation to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, in theſe three things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Look at and fix your Eye on unſeen things, this is the firſt. Chriſtians, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to look at things which are not ſeen, above, beyond, and paſt all that is now in ſight, over all that is preſent, to the future and unſeen Death and Judgment, Heaven and Hell, that are yet out of ſight, yet unſeen. Conſider, this looking at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things will be of very great Advantage to you on many Accounts; it's your Duty, as you have ſeen, and it will be your Gain and for your Good, as you may ſee, if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe ſeven or eight things: this looking at unſeen things will help very much,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To mortify your Hearts to ſeen things, to the World and the things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Seen things are full of Snares, the World has been the Deſtruction of a world of Souls; it's a bleſſed thing to have a Heart that is looſe from, and dead to it: Any thing that tends to part, and keep the Heart and the World aſunder, deſerves to have a Room and Place in our Hearts. Now nothing is more ſovereign in this Caſe, than a cloſe and conſtant practice of this propoſed Duty, a looking at unſeen things.
<hi>Aeternis inhianti in faſtidio ſunt omnia tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitoria;</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:63794:61"/> He that looks at unſeen eternal Things, will make light of ſeen temporal Things; this will take Affections off things below, up to things above. It's ſaid, that the great Cities of <hi>Campania</hi> ſeem but ſmall Cottages, to them that ſtand on the top of the <hi>Alps:</hi> So truly all the great and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and precious things of the World, that ſo many Eyes admire, and ſo many Hearts dote on, all the Thrones, Crowns, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Profits, Beauties, Braveries, and Glories of this World, ſeem but little to them that have an Eye looking at that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Vail. If you look but a little upon the Sun, why when you look down again upon the Earth, you can ſcarce for a time ſee any thing of all the things about you; the Light and Beauty of that which you have ſeen, makes theſe things diſappear: Why ſo, a looking at unſeen things, will hugely darken and leſſen ſeen things in our Eye, and make that we ſhall ſee little in them to be much ſet by. Some Writers ſay, that after <hi>Lazarus</hi> was raiſed from the Dead, he was never ſeen to ſmile, or make any matter of the Matters of the World; he had ſeen that which did keep his Heart dead to theſe things, as poor and worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. My Beloved, if we might ſuppoſe, that ſome of the Saints now in Heaven ſhould be ſent back again to us in this World, what would they do? how would they look on all theſe things? Do you <pb n="106" facs="tcp:63794:62"/> think they'd be taken with them, or preſs after them? (1.) Would they fall in love with your Houſes, or Fields, or Gardens? (2.) Would they ſet by your Gold and Silver? (3.) Would they make any thing of that you make moſt of? Surely, no, the whole World would be no other than a Wilderneſs to them; they that tread the Sun, the Moon, and the Stars under their Feet, would ſurely trample all that is ſpecious in the Earth under their Feet as ſo much Dung. And as they would make nothing, ſo ſurely Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians (who are going to ſhare with them) would make leſs than ordinarily they do of all ſeen things, if they looked but more to unſeen things, to the Place and Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Saints in Light. Wouldſt thou be accompanied with a mortified Heart to the World; (1.) To the Luſts of the World; (2.) To the Pleaſures of the World; (3.) To the greatneſs of the World; (4.) To the Gain; (5.) To the Glory of the World? then look, look at unſeen things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It will help to make you Content in every Condition, (this another) and with whatſoever is your Portion in this World. The Holy Apoſtle had his Converſation in Heaven; Philip. 3.20. <hi>For our Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And had learned,</hi> Chap. 4.11. <hi>in whatſoever ſtate he was, therewith to be Content.</hi> His Converſe with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <pb n="107" facs="tcp:63794:62"/> had taught him to be Content with his Condition on Earth. O Sirs, believing views of the things above, that a Believer is going to, are enough to make a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſay, when in the worſt, moſt needy and wanting outward Condition in the World, with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 16.6.
<hi>The Lines are fallen to me in pleaſant Places; yea, I have a goodly Heritage:</hi> yonder's better Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, where there is no Curſe, no Night, no Hunger; yonder Inheritance that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, undefiled, and that fadeth not away; yonder Kingdom, Crown, and weight of Glory will make amends for all. Wants are now hanging on me, but I ſhall want nothing when I am come to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Houſe, to the new Heavens, and the new Earth, to the pure River of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Life, and to the Tree of Life in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God; all will be well in the World to come, and I ſhall have enough when I am called to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-Supper of the Lamb, and brought to eat and drink continually at his Table in his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I remember <hi>Jerome,</hi> comforting a young Hermite that was ſad, bade him look up to Heaven, <hi>&amp; Paradiſum mente deambulare,</hi> and ſays he, <hi>tamdiu in Eremo non eris:</hi> So may I ſay to you that fear God, when you are in a Wilderneſs, when Wants are on you, and diſcontented Paſſions are ready to riſe, then look up to Heaven, look at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen <pb n="108" facs="tcp:63794:63"/> things, and ſo long you'l not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content; the Thoughts of ſeeing God, and following the Lamb whitherſoever he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, will be enough to make you at Peace with your preſent States.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It will help to leſſen all the Loſſes of the World, and of ſeen things. The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Hebrews</hi> did not only bear the ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Goods, but took it joyfully, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. But how came it to be thus? how came they to take this ſo chearfully, that has broken the Heart of many a one in the World? Why their Eyes were looking upwards as high as Heaven, and the things of Heaven took away their Diſcontent;
<hi>knowing in your ſelves that you have in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a better and an enduring Subſtance.</hi> Mark, their Eye, the Eye of Faith and Hope was on the Eternal Riches in Heaven's keeping for them; and this was their Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this made them, <hi>non modo aequis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis ſed etiam laetis,</hi> to take their Loſſes. Do Loſſes come upon me? do I loſe this, and that, and the other Comfort and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment? why, while I look at things not ſeen; (1.) I ſee I ſhall not need them. (2.) I ſee I ſhall have better in the Room of them. (3.) I ſee I ſhall have Comfort that will not be loſable. When the <hi>Danites</hi> had taken away <hi>Micah</hi>'s Idols, and Prieſt, he cries out after them, Judges 18.24. <hi>What have I more?</hi> that is, (as tho he had ſaid) you have taken all, you have left me no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:63794:63"/> thus it may be with a carnal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he may loſe this to day, and that to morrow, and ſo on till it come to this, <hi>what have I more?</hi> Ay, but it can never come to this with a gracious Perſon, let Loſſes come on him as thick and as faſt as on <hi>Job;</hi> yet after, and at the End of all, he can look up and ſay, I have a Treaſure more, I have a Crown more, I have an everlaſting Kingdom more, I have a whole World more, out of ſight and danger too; that and the other thing is gone, but it's not Chriſt, it's not Heaven, Chriſt is left, and Heaven is left: and this now cannot but very much leſſen any Loſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It will help to lighten all the Croſſes and Afflictions in the World. Our Saviour himſelf went through the Sufferings and Shame of the World, with an Eye ſet on the Joy ſet before him: Heb. 12.2. <hi>Who for the Joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſs, deſpiſing the Shame, and is ſet down at the right Hand of the Throne of God.</hi> Mark pray, for the lightning of the Croſs, and Shame, he took the Joy in his Eye, and this Joy in his Eye took the Weight out of the Croſs, and the Shame out of the Shame of the World, <hi>for the Joy that was ſet before him.</hi> And Chriſtians are here called to look at him herein, as their Pattern and Example that they are to follow in like Caſes, <hi>looking at Jeſus the Author and finiſher of our Faith.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <pb n="110" facs="tcp:63794:64"/> here in this Place had their Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings lightned by this; in the Verſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going the Text, you have them weighing their Affliction and finding it light, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring their Affliction and finding it ſhort: but how came it to be thus in their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count? why this you have in the Text, <hi>While we look not at things which are ſeen which are Temporal, but at things which are not ſeen which are Eternal:</hi> their preſent and ſeen Affliction was light, while they weighed it with the Weight of unſeen Glory, and it was likewiſe ſhort while they meaſured it with the Eternity of unſeen Glory. O Sirs, there's enough in unſeen things to lighten any Croſs, Suffering, or Affliction a Chriſtian can come under, and to make him quiet, ſilent, and patient under all: the unſeen things of Heaven are enough to quiet, the unſeen things of Hell are enough to ſilence under all: look, Soul, but either of theſe ways when thou art go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under any Croſs, and ſo long ſure it cannot be heavy on thee; are Sufferings now on thee? look at the Priſon, Chains, Darkneſs, Worm, Fire of the Damned, what they are ſuffering on whom God is raining Snares, Fire, Brimſtone, and an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Tempeſt; and thou canſt not think them heavy: or look at the Reſt, Joy, Goodneſs, Glory, laid up for the Saints in Heaven, and thou canſt not but ſay with the Apoſtle, Rom. 8.18. <hi>For I reckon that <pb n="111" facs="tcp:63794:64"/> the Sufferings of this preſent Life, are not worthy to be compared with the Glory that ſhall be revealed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. It will be a remedy againſt all Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: while
<hi>Moſes</hi> his Eye was upon the recompence of Reward, the Riches, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and the Pleaſures of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court were eaſily overlook'd. Heb. 11.25, 26, 27. <hi>Chuſing rather to ſuffer Affliction with the People of God, than to enjoy the Pleaſures of Sin for a Seaſon; eſteeming the Reproaches of Chriſt greater Riches than the Treaſures in</hi> Egypt: <hi>for he had reſpect to the recompence of Reward. By Faith he forſook</hi> Egypt, <hi>not fearing the Wrath of the King; for he endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as ſeeing him who is inviſible.</hi> This ſets a Chriſtian above Temptation as it were, it mortifies to the World as before; and this is commonly the Matter of Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the great Baits that Satan makes uſe of are the things of the World; he tempts ſometimes with the Beauty, ſometimes with the Gain, ſometimes with the Glory, and ordinarily with ſomething or other of the World. Now, I ſay, this looking to things unſeen, helps to crucify to the World the Matter of Temptation, and ſo is a ſpecial Antidote againſt Temptation; for when the Heart is dead to the Matter of a Temptation, it will not eaſily faſten on the Tempted: beſides, the looking at unſeen things brings greater things into ſight, than any that can be preſented in a <pb n="112" facs="tcp:63794:65"/> Temptation. Does the Tempter come with ſpecious and alluring Temptations, as he came to our Saviour with all the Kingdoms of the World, and all the Glory of them? why an Eye ſet on unſeen things, ſees greater things than all the Kingdoms of the World, and the Glory of them. Doth he come with terrifying and affrighting Temptations, as Bonds, or Baniſhment, or Tortures? why an Eye ſet on unſeen things, ſees worſer: Unſeen Glory in Heaven is greater than all the ſeen Excellencies on Earth; and unſeen Torments in Hell are worſe than all the ſeen Tortures of this Life. This is another Privilege of looking at unſeen things; would you be out of the way of Temptations, Temptations that have caſt many a one down, and coſt them much of their Peace and Comfort in the World? then be much in this Duty, keep an Eye on unſeen things. When a Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion comes in its Power, look before you as far as Death, as Judgment, as Heaven, as Hell; and while theſe are in your Eye, they'l keep your Heart and the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aſunder. As long as the Bird keeps above in the Air, ſhe is out of the way of Snares, her falling into theſe is by lighting on the Earth.</p>
            <p n="6">6. A ſingular Remedy againſt Sin in theſe ſinning Times, wherein Iniquity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds: <hi>Solomon</hi> preſcribes this to young Men, Eccleſ. 11.9. <hi>Rejoice, O young Man, <pb n="113" facs="tcp:63794:65"/> in thy Youth, and let thy Heart chear thee in the Days of thy Youth; and walk in the ways of thy Heart, and in the ſight of thine Eyes: but know thou, that for all theſe things God will bring thee to Judgment.</hi> Mark, that they may be ſtopped in theſe Courſes, he calls them to look over their preſent ways, to the unſeen Judgment before them. O Sirs, theſe unſeen, unſeen things have much weight in them, if Chriſtians would but carry them on their Hearts, and look at them when Sin is at the Door. I have read of a young Woman, who being preſſed by a Gallant to gratify his Luſts, anſwered him, if you'l but grant me one requeſt I will do what you deſire: What is that ſaid he again? why, ſaith ſhe, it's but this, do but hold your Finger one Hour in the Blaze of this Candle: he replied, No: then ſaid ſhe, will you not for my ſake hold your Finger one Hour in this Candle, and would you have me throw my ſelf into an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Fire for you? and this ſilenced him. Why Chriſtians, pray try this Courſe, when Sin is at the Door, when you are ready to go out to any Evil, take unſeen things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Eye, look at Death, Judgment, Heaven, and Hell; and ſee if you can, if you dare meet or meddle with that Sin, with theſe in ſight, or while they are in ſight: Surely, Sirs, this would be a mighty great Preſervative: and if you would but walk more as ſeeing things inviſible, <pb n="114" facs="tcp:63794:66"/> you ſhould be more undefiled in the Way.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It will make you more fit to live any where, in any Place, among any kind of Perſons. He that hath filled his Eye with unſeen things, is prepared to live among a Generation, (1.) Of profane Creatures, without being drawn to run with them to the ſame exceſs of Riot. (2.) Among a Company of Worldlings, that are crying up the Mammon of Unrighteouſneſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being enticed to approve their way by ſeeing them hurry and rake this World together by all means. (3.) Among Perſons of mutable and temporizing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that are off and on, one thing at one time, another at another time: he that looks at unſeen things, has that in his Eyes which will keep him one and the ſame at all times, and in all Places; a <hi>Noah</hi> in the old World, a <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom,</hi> a <hi>Job</hi> in
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z;</hi> a God-fearing Perſon whereever he comes or is caſt.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Looking at unſeen things will make you more willing to die, and go to the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of unſeen things: whence is it that many Chriſtians are ſo loth to leave and go from ſeen things, to part with ſeen Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and ſeen Poſſeſſions, and ſeen Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts? is it not from a want of lively Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, and believing Views of the unſeen Proviſions made for them in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? I remember I have read of a devout
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:63794:66"/> Pilgrim travelling to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who in his way paſſing through many Cities, and ſeeing many rare and choice Monuments, yet took no content in any thing that he ſaw, but would ſtill ſay, this is not <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> this is not <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> why ſo truly if we had but our Eye as the Apoſtle, on things unſeen, we ſhould among all our ſeen Comforts, ſay, this is not Heaven, this is not ſeeing of God, ſeeing his Face, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him Face to Face; this is not being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne, this is not the inheriting of all things; and our Hearts and Souls would be more there, more ſet on going thither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> This may ſerve to exhort us to prepare for unſeen things, for a ſeeing of things yet unſeen: are there ſuch? O then, Sirs, let it be your great Matter now Day and Night, Night and Day, to get into a readineſs for a comfortable ſeeing of theſe things which are not ſeen. This is the next word I would leave with you, I pray take it up into your Practice, and make it your Work. Heb. 11.7. <hi>By Faith</hi> Noah
<hi>being warned of God of things not ſeen as yet, moved with Fear, prepared an Ark to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of his Houſe.</hi> My Beloved, I may ſay to you, (1.) You have been warned of God this Day (by the Hand of one of his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers) of things not ſeen as yet. (2.) You have been told that theſe things not ſeen as yet, are certain and great, greater than
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:63794:67"/> the things that <hi>Noah</hi> was warned of, and unavoidable, and near, and Eternal: O do as <hi>Noah</hi> here in this Caſe did, <hi>i. e.</hi> (1.) Believe the coming of theſe things not ſeen as yet. (2.) Fear, fear being taken unready by them at their Coming. And (3.) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare an Ark to the ſaving of your ſelves; make Proviſion, timely Proviſion for the Coming of theſe things; that as <hi>Noah</hi> and his Houſe were ſaved when the Deluge came, ſo you may be ſaved in the Day when theſe things begin to come to paſs. I might tell you, (1.) That you are warned of them for this. (2.) That you are called to this, to prepare an Ark. (3.) That you have Means and Helps betruſted with you for this. (4.) That you have your Time for this. (5.) That you muſt not tarry long with ſeen things (6.) That dreadful things will come in ſight, and continue for ever in ſight, if you have no Ark, no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion ready. (7.) That glorious things will appear at th s Appearing of things not ſeen as yet, to them that have made due and ſeaſonable Preparation for them; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let me give you a word by way of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: If you ſay, but how may we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare an Ark to the ſaving of our ſelves? How may we provide and get into ſuch readineſs as when unſeen things come into ſight, we may ſee God? Why in a word I would tell you;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:63794:67"/>1ſt. Negatively.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſeen things will be no Proviſion for unſeen things, will not ſerve to meet them with. I pray you take notice of it, they are ſeen things now that we ſpend moſt of our Time on, that we lay out moſt of our Care about, that we make the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtir about; yet alas, I tell you, none of them all, neither one, nor another, will be Proviſion to meet theſe unſeen things with. Dear Sirs, when you have done all that ever you can, and laid up the ſeen things together, they'l all ſerve for and ſignify nothing; you cannot, you cannot meet Death with Houſes and Lands, you cannot go to Judgment with Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, you can't go to Heaven by Maſter, and Sir, by Titles and Greatneſs among your Neighbours: think a little of it, I pray, with your ſelves when alone, ſeen things will be no Proviſion for unſeen, they may be your undoing when you come to enter on unſeen, as they have been to many thouſands who are gone before, but they can't be any Proviſion for them: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this, while you are hurrying up and down among ſeen things for ſeen things, you are wearying your ſelves for things that will not profit when unſeen things come upon you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Only unſeen things are Proviſion for unſeen things: things that will ſerve to <pb n="118" facs="tcp:63794:68"/> meet them with, as an Intereſt in Chriſt, a new Creature, a pure Heart, a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, a Treaſure of ſaving Grace laid in; theſe are the things that will be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion to meet the things not yet ſeen with. When the Flood came upon the old World, Houſes, and Lands, and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and Multitudes of Friends, and all ſeen things they had about were nothing; many a one then periſhed, that had a fine Houſe, a fair Eſtate, that was living in the midſt of Pomp and Pleaſure, and Plenty; and only <hi>Noah</hi> and his Houſe that had the Ark, and were got into it, were ſaved. So, Sirs, when theſe things begin to come into ſight, all ſeen things (as I have ſaid) will be nothing; it will be all one, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have Houſes or no Houſes, Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es or Rags, all will be if you have the Ark, <hi>i. e.</hi> if you have Chriſt, if you be in him; only this, an Intereſt in Chriſt will carry through unſeen Death, through unſeen Judgment, and to unſeen Glory, to the new Heavens, and the new Earth, to the Throne of God and of the Lamb, to the Temple of God, to the Crown of Life, the Kingdom of Heaven, and the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of all things. 1 John 5.12. <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life, and he that hath not the Son hath not Life;</hi> Life in Death, Life at Judgment, Life in Glory, and ſhall live with God for ever. This, this is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion <pb n="119" facs="tcp:63794:68"/> that will not fail. So that if you would be in readineſs for this ſeeing of unſeen things, ſee that you get into the Ark, I ſay; that you hang not about it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a general Profeſſion, but that you come into it; that you get a Poſſeſſion of Chriſt, a part in Chriſt, and then you are ſafe; then, and never till then you ſhall be ready. A Man in a Market is then rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to go Home when he has done all his Buſineſs that he came about, when he has bought in Proviſion for his Houſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo a Perſon is then ready for this great opening of unſeen things, when all his Time and worldly Buſineſſes are ended, and his Proviſion for Eternity are in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs; and this is when he is got into the Ark, Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We may hence be exhorted, to deſire and ſeek to come to the ſeeing of theſe unſeen things. This is the third Word. (1.) Look at; (2.) Prepare for; (3.) Seek and long to go to the ſeeing of them. If looking at them was ſuch a Cordial and Corroboration to the Apoſtles among their many Preſſures: O then what, what is this ſeeing, the enjoying of them? It's ſaid of the Patriarchs, that they were Strangers and Pilgrims, Heb.
11.13. <hi>Theſe all died in Faith, not having received the Promiſes, but having ſeen them afar off, and were perſwaded of them, and embraced
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:63794:69"/> them, and confeſſed that they were Strangers and Pilgrims on the Earth. Ver.</hi> 16. They deſired <hi>a better Countrey.</hi> Of <hi>Abraham, Ver.</hi> 10. 'tis ſaid, <hi>he looked for a City that had Foundations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why on this Faſhion Chriſtians, (1.) Live as Strangers and Pilgrims on the Earth. (2.) Seek a City, and look for a better Countrey. (3.) Deſire to go to ſee the things that God hath prepared.</p>
            <p>O methinks this News of unſeen things ſhould ſet afoot great Deſires, Longings, and Breathings in Chriſtians after Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, where they are to be ſeen. But O the Unbelief and Carnality that lodges in us! if we were told of wonderful things that were fallen to us in far Countries, (1.) What haſte would we make towards them? (2.) How loth would we be to tarry from them? (3.) How long ſhould we think it e're we came to them? But alas, the Holy Ghoſt hath made great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries to us, to us of glorious things within the Vail, of Crowns, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and Reſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet we, we lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger here among unſeen things, make little haſte towards unſeen things, or think it long that we are from them. Pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, in a word, Chriſtians, that your Deſires after this ſeeing of unſeen things may be warmed and raiſed, I ſay, conſider theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:63794:69"/>1. Who and what is there (<hi>viz.</hi> in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) this may quicken you to this longing for: I may tell you,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That all your beſt Friends are there, your Father is there, and your Chriſt is there, and your Comforter is there, and your Brethren are there; all the Sons, and all the Daughters of God, who have been going hence from <hi>Adam</hi> to this Day, are gone thither, and are now there. Is it not very deſirable to go to, and to be with them? Where ſhould a Child of God chuſe or deſire to be, if not there where his Father and all his beſt Friends are?</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Conſider that your beſt Eſtate is there; as your beſt Friends live, ſo your beſt Eſtate lies there, your Reſt, your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, your Crown, your Kingdom, your World, and all lies there. It may be, (1.) Here you have no Reſt, and there you ſhall have no Labour. (2.) Here you have Shame, and there you ſhall have a Crown of Glory. (3.) Here you have no Inheritance, not ſo much as whereon to ſet a Foot, or at moſt but a poor, narrow, and dirty one, full of Incumbrances; there you have a full and fair Inheritance. (4.) Here you are pent up in a narrow Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs; there you have a whole Kingdom, a World of your own to turn you to; where ſhould you deſire and chuſe to be?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:63794:70"/>(3.) Your everlaſting Home is there, your eternal Abode, the Place where you ſhall be for ever and ever. Here you are as Strangers in a Foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as Travellers in an Inn; there's your Countrey, there's your Home; how ſhould you long to be there! This is one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider what there is not, what you ſhall not ſee there. The Jews that were left of the Captivity, were ſet on going into
<hi>Egypt,</hi> becauſe there they hoped to be exempted from the Dangers and Wants that attended them in their preſent Station: Jer. 42.14. <hi>We will go into</hi> Egypt, <hi>where we ſhall ſee no War, nor hear of the ſound of the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, nor have hunger of Bread, and there will we dwell.</hi> O Sirs, how ſhould Saints be ſet on going for Heaven, where they ſhall ſee no War, nor hunger of Bread! O think of it. (1.) There you ſhall ſee no Luſts to entice; (2.) No Devil to tempt; (3.) No World to ſeduce; (4.) No Afflictions to load; (5.) No Labours to weary; (6.) No Cares to perplex; (7.) No Loſſes to vex; (8.) No Evils to exerciſe and diſquiet: All theſe things that are now ſeen, ſhall then be unſeen things for ever. Saints now in Heaven are ſeeing none of them, ſhall never ſee any of them again for ever. Do you now, <pb n="123" facs="tcp:63794:70"/> Sirs, conflict with all, or moſt of theſe, Day after Day? Do you groan and ſigh under, are your Lives imbitter'd by them? Why ſhould you not long then to be at the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things, where theſe will be unſeen for ever?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider what you ſhall ſee there. But how can I tell you this? They are unſeen things that are to be ſeen there; beyond all that hath been ſeen, and paſt all that can be thought by the Sons of Men! Expect not to be told, till you come to ſee: Only I may tell you, that when you are come to the ſeeing theſe unſeen things; Then,</p>
            <p n="1">1. You ſhall ſee God; John 1.18. <hi>No Man hath ſeen God at any time; the only begotten Son which is in the Boſom of the Father, he hath declar'd him.</hi> A ſight of God is beyond all that is attainable here: But there you ſhall ſee him Face to Face: 1 Cor. 13.12. <hi>For now we ſee through a Glaſs darkly, but then Face to Face: Now I know in part, but then ſhall I know, even as alſo I am known.</hi> Then <hi>(i. e.)</hi> in Heaven, 1 John 3.2. <hi>But we know that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him; for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> You ſhall then ſee the Divine Eſſence, the Trinity of Perſons, the great Myſtery, God manifeſt in the <pb n="124" facs="tcp:63794:71"/> Fleſh, the perſonal Union of the two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the Son of God, the glorious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of God. 1. His almighty Power. 2. His infinite Wiſdom. 3. His bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Goodneſs. 4. His bottomleſs Mercy. 5. His endleſs Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And O this will be another manner of Sight than any that ever has come in ſight!</p>
            <p n="2">2. You ſhall ſee the Angels, the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God; 1. Their infinite Number; 2. Their beautiful Order; 3. Their bleſſed Work; 4. Their glorious Properties and Perfections. O what a ſight will this be! If when only one Angel appeared to the Shepherds (in his Night-clothes, as I may ſay) they were ſurrounded with ſo great Glory, that it's ſaid,
<hi>Luke</hi> 2.9. <hi>The Glory of the Lord ſhone round about them,</hi> that is, a tranſcendent and ſurpaſſing Glory; I ſay, if the preſence of one Angel was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſo great a Glory, then what will it be to ſee the thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands that miniſter to Chriſt, and the ten thouſand times ten thouſand that fall down before him!</p>
            <p n="3">3. You ſhall ſee all the Saints of God, all that are gone to God, and are with God this Day in Glory. If, my Beloved, but one of theſe were ſent from Heaven; if but <hi>Abraham,</hi> or <hi>Moſes,</hi> or
<hi>David,</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> 
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:63794:71"/> or <hi>Paul,</hi> ſhould come again into this World, how far would you not go to ſee this one? When <hi>Lazarus</hi> was raiſed from the Dead, it's ſaid,
<hi>John</hi> 12.9. <hi>And they came not for Jeſus ſake only, but that they might ſee</hi> Lazarus <hi>alſo, whom he had raiſed from the Dead.</hi> The rarity of the ſight, <hi>viz.</hi> a Man that had been in, that was come out of another World, brought ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from far and near: Why ſo would you not go a great way to ſee ſuch a Man? Why how willing then ſhould you be to go to Heaven, where you ſhall come to ſee, not one but all the Patriarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, Confeſſors and Saints out of every Nation under Heaven: Here you ſhall ſee <hi>Abraham,</hi> and
<hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi> here Parents ſhall ſee their Children again, and Children their Parents; Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands ſhall ſee their Wives again, and Wives their Husbands; Paſtors ſhall ſee their People again, and People their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quos modo miramus Regione videbimus illa,</l>
               <l>Et veteres inter fuſcipiemus Avos.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Bapt. Mantuanus.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>And you ſhall not only ſee them thus, but ſee them without all thoſe Afflictions, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, Blemiſhes, Corruptions, Imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Infirmities that did accompany <pb n="126" facs="tcp:63794:72"/> them in this State, and clothed with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Perfections.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You ſhall ſee all thoſe great things, which the great God hath prepared for his Saints before the Foundation of the World; the things that are (as before) ſet out by the Names and Titles of a better Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<hi>Paradiſe, a Houſe, a City, an Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Crown, Kingdom,</hi> and the reſt. You ſhall ſee all, all theſe, all the things wherein the Purpoſes and Counſels of the Father, the Purchaſes and Performances of the Son, the Workings and Operations of the Spirit, meet in their Perfection, and have their full, perfect, and eternal Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Conſummation. O who would not long for ſuch a ſight? Who would be unwilling to go from ſeeing Sin, and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and Want, to ſee ſuch a ſight as this for ever?</p>
            <p n="5">5. I might further tell you, that you ſhall there ſee a clear and ſatisfying Reſolution of all hard and doubtful Queſtions, a full determination of the voluminous Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies and Diſputations about the great Myſteries of Election, Redemption, Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, Sanctification, the Reſurrection, Conſummation, Judgment,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:63794:72"/>6. A plain and full Expoſition of all dark and obſcure Places in the Scripture; the true and full meaning of every Text, even thoſe that now the numerous and voluminous Commentaries of the moſt learned and eminent Writers of all Ages, leave us in the dark about. There are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, things hard to be underſtood; and
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Knots that cannot be untied: But then dark things ſhall be perfectly clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and doubtful things fully reſolved to a plenary Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>This is the third thing, to exhort us to deſire and ſeek to come to the ſeeing of theſe unſeen things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
